<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A legacy for saints; being several experiences of the dealings of God with Anna Trapnel, in, and after her conversion, (written some years since with her own hand) and new coming to the sight of some friends, they have judged them worthy of publike view; together with some letters of a latter date, sent to the congregation with whom she walks in the fellowship of the Gospel, and to some other friends.</title>
            <author>Trapnel, Anna.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94794</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2032</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E806_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207169</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866238</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866238</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118503</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94794)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118503)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 123:E806[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A legacy for saints; being several experiences of the dealings of God with Anna Trapnel, in, and after her conversion, (written some years since with her own hand) and new coming to the sight of some friends, they have judged them worthy of publike view; together with some letters of a latter date, sent to the congregation with whom she walks in the fellowship of the Gospel, and to some other friends.</title>
                  <author>Trapnel, Anna.</author>
                  <author>Proud, John, fl. 1654.</author>
                  <author>Ingold, Caleb.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for T. Brewster, at the three Bibles in Pauls Church-yard, near London-House,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Edited by John Proud and Caleb Ingold. Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 24.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trapnel, Anna --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conversion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118503:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LEGACY FOR SAINTS; BEING SEVERAL EXPERIENCES of the dealings of God with Anna Trapnel, In, and after her Converſion, (written ſome years ſince with her own hand) and now coming to the ſight of ſome friends, they have judged them worthy of publike view: Together with ſome Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of a latter date, ſent to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation with whom ſhe walks in the fellowſhip of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and to ſome other FRIENDS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, for <hi>T. Brewſter,</hi> at the three Bibles in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, near <hi>London</hi>-Houſe, 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:118503:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118503:2"/>
            <head>To all that fear the Lord, under what form ſoever, who have fellowſhip with the Father, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt; The Church of God uſually meeting in Great <hi>Al-Hallows, London,</hi> (whereof Mr. <hi>John Simpſon</hi> is Teacher) ſendeth greeting.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome Experiences of <hi>Anna Trapnell,</hi> our dea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Siſter, now Priſoner in <hi>Bridewel,</hi> coming to our hands, we have peruſed and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; And although the various and wonderful dealings of God with her ſoul (known to many of us) for divers years laſt paſt, are not herein mentioned, (as ſhe intended, but was prevented by her preſent troubles) nevertheleſs, by our own hearts, we judge this ſmall Legacy will be of much price and uſe to the Lords people: And ſeeing the malice of Satan, and hard meaſure from men, have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to bury her, both name, profeſſion, (and
<pb facs="tcp:118503:3"/>if poſſible) ſpirit in her, whileſt ſhe yet lives, (and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e think leans on her Lords boſom.) Therefore is this Legacy now adminiſtred, which otherwiſe had wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the death of the Teſtatr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>x, as ſhe fully purpoſed.</p>
            <p>All we conceive neceſſary to be ſaid by us, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Legacy it ſelf, is onely to give our Teſtimony, ſo far as we have knowledge (as our duty to God, and to his hand-maid obligeth us) to the reality of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences therein mentioned: whereof divers of us have been eye, and ear witneſſes, and were with our Siſter at ſeveral ſeaſons, when ſhe was under thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular dealings of God. We purpoſely forbear to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large our commendations, becauſe we apprehend this kinde of Subject is always beſt commended by that preſence and efficacy of God which he pleaſeth to afford; and alſo, becauſe we would not in the leaſt degree infringe your liberty, to taſt and try what ſpirit and excellency is in it, and ſo to judge freely (yet with ſeriouſneſs, as having to do with God therein) what entertainment and eſteem it deſerves: we are alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged by our duty, to give you ſome account of the perſon, by whom this Lagacy is bequeathed, who is indeed under much reproach and miſrepreſentation among all ſorts of people; and we apprehend we might without offence ſay, made a ſpectacle to the whole Land, being rendred a Contemner of Scriptures, of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and of late, as one of a vile Converſation; For her preſent impriſonment at <hi>Bridewel</hi> (if it were not ſo intended) cannot but ſuggeſt extream ſcandal, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs touching her, to all that hear thereof, though
<pb facs="tcp:118503:3"/>we that know her, and the cauſe for which ſhe is laid there, are not aſhamed of her, or it, and hope we never ſhall be, which is all we ſhall now ſay to that: Onely give us leave briefly to impart (for your ſatisfaction) what we have known of her, for we have had commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with her in the light, love, ſpirit and ordinances of the Goſpel, divers years, and to this day alſo, ſo far as we can obtain it, for the reſtraint ſhe is now under; and are able to ſay, in oppoſition to what ſhe is aſperſed with, That</p>
            <p n="1">1. She hath the Scriptures in very great regard; as that holy word which hath flowed from God, by men who had extraordinary inſpiration and ability to give it forth, according to what hath been apprehended among the moſt ſober and ſpiritual Saints from time to time, concerning the ſame; with the excellency whereof ſhe profeſſeth her ſelf much raviſhed, making it her buſineſs to ſtudy, and to live in the power and ſpirit of them: whoſe profeſſion and principles, having ſuffered many aſſaults and temptations herein, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains exceedingly confirmed in her perſwaſions of, and love to the truth, holineſs, authority, and precious uſefulneſs of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. She is for the ſpiritual exerciſe of all the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God, to the uttermoſt degree of light ſhe enjoys; againſt Ranters, profane Notioniſts, and all ſorts of men of ſcornful opinions to the contrary: for which we have not onely her word, but her practice with us, which doth beſt expreſs any ones principle.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118503:4"/>
            <p>And touching the Miniſtry (becauſe in relation thereunto alſo, a very hard ſentence is paſt upon her) there is this to be offered in vindication of her; that her principle is plain and firm for it, and that ſhe doth much love and reverence, own all Miniſters that enter in by the door, and have the true unction; her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfaction is onely to that ſtanding, and inſtitution which hath been by Biſhops (it being derived from <hi>Rome</hi>) or ſuch as are evidently after that pattern; and that alſo without the leaſt prejudice to the grace of God in any.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Her converſation (for any thing that ever came to our knowledge) we muſt teſtifie hath been very beautiful and unblameable: exceeding unworthy of thoſe black mouths which have been opened againſt it, and of thoſe injurious hands ſhe hath fallen into.</p>
            <p>We might ſay much of her tender conſcience, her ſweet, meek, ſober, exemplary temper, and impartial love to all Saints: and alſo her freedom and deſire to have communion with them upon that old, large, and univerſal principle of Saintſhip and union with Chriſt, wherein we know her to be very excellent, as ſome letters of her own (which we have thought our duty to make publike) will more effectually declare, then we are able.</p>
            <p>This ſhort Teſtimony we have thought fit to ſend abroad with this Legacy and Letters of our dear Sister, for the exoneration of our duty to God, to
<pb facs="tcp:118503:4"/>her, and to your ſouls, which we would not have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed (by any hard thoughts that reports may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, concerning the perſon whoſe it is) to re<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p the fruit, and refreſhment which (our god bleſſing) may redound thereby.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Dated <date>the 9. of the 5. moneth 1654.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Signed in the name, and by appointment of the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, in the abſence of our Teacher, by <hi>Iohn Proud</hi> Elder, <hi>Caleb Ingold</hi> Decon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:118503:5"/>
            <head>Reader, thou art deſired before thou readeſt this ſmall Legacy, to take notice of theſe few faults, and mend them, which by reaſon of the difficulty of the Copy, being old written and torn, have eſcaped the Preſs.</head>
            <p>AS in page 15. line 6. for Aninomian, read <hi>Antinomian,</hi> p. 24. l. 19. r. <hi>the ſoul is made,</hi> p. 30. l. 1. for from r. <hi>for,</hi> p. 31. l. 31. for men r. <hi>me,</hi> p. 33. l. 27. for 3 Joh. r. 1. p. 35. l. 8. for words, r. <hi>worlds,</hi> p. 38. l. 31. for the 40. of <hi>Iſa</hi> r. 29. p. 41. l. 2. for <hi>Ioh</hi> 1. 14. r. 14. <hi>and</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118503:5"/>
            <head>A LEGACY FOR SAINTS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome experiences of the workings of God in legall convictions, and in the time of childhood. Firſt, When a child, then the Lord awed my Spirit, and for the leaſt treſpaſs, my heart was ſmitten, and though my godly mother did not ſee me offend, that ſhe might reprove me, which ſhe was ready to do, being ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the honour of her beloved Saviour, even for the leaſt ſecret ſin, that the world calls a trifle; though I thought it nothing, yet ſtill the all-ſeeing [eye] watched my ways, and he called to me, though I knew him not, yet he kept me<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and his banner over me was love; and though my nature was as corrupt as any, a child of wrath as well as others, and forward to do evill, and backward to that which is good, yet ſtill I was under the awaking of <hi>J<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ehovah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, when I was about 14. years of age, I began to be very eager and forward to hear and pray, though in a very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall manner; Thus I went on ſome years, and then I roſe to a higher pitch, to a more ſp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ritu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l condition, as I thought, and I followed after that Miniſtry that was moſt preſſed after by the ſtricteſt Profeſſors, and I <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an with great violence, having a great zeal, though not according to knowledge, and I appeared a very high grown Chriſtian in the thoughts of many, I had great parts, in prayer great inlargements, and in diſcou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſing and repeating of Sermons, I was very forward, and did it with great delight
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118503:6"/>and affection, and much trembling of ſpirit was upon me, but I was in all this very legall, and yet more legall; providence or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that I ſhould hear Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> ſpeak from thoſe words, in the 26. of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the 20. verſe, <hi>Come my people, enter thou into thy chambers, and ſhut thy doors about thee, hide thy ſelf as it were for a little moment, until the indignation be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt.</hi> From theſe words he opened the marriage Covenant that is between God and his Spouſe; from that word. <hi>Come,</hi> he ſhewed the ſweet compellation of God, to his Covenanted people; then I was convinced of the excellency of that condition, to be in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and to know it upon good grounds, which I was very ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of; and though I thought my ſelf in a very good condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before, yet now it ſeized upon my ſpirit, that ſurely I was not in the Covenant, and if I were, I ſhould know it; and I ſtill cryed out, oh what ſhall I do to know it! without the knowledge of God, to be my God, I am undone; my ſpirit is filled with hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and the terrors of the Law exceedingly oppreſſed me, and I ran from Miniſter to Miniſter, from Sermon to Sermon, but I could find no reſt; I could not be contented to hear once or twice in the week; but I muſt hear from the firſt day to the laſt, and thought that not enough neither; and if I had not ſhed ſome tears in a Sermon, I then went home full of horror, concluding my ſelf to be that ſtony ground Chriſt ſpake of in the parable of the ſower; I apprehended Divine diſpleaſure againſt me, leaving me in a feared condition, giving me over to blindneſs of mind, and hardneſs of heart for ever; and when I have been hindred from hearing a Sermon which I deſired to hear, I have concluded that I might have received Chriſt in that Sermon, which being ſhut out from, I was ſhut out from Chriſt, that being the time that Chriſt ſhould have been tendred to me, the which I miſt, and ſo ſhould be without Chriſt for ever. Such bondage I was under, that had I neglected a duty, or an opportunity of hearing, though a lawfull occaſion hindred, and I could not be ſaid to neglect, yet it ſorely ſeized upon me, that I had; And I was damn'd, one ſet a part for deſtruction, and I was ſtrongly tempted to deſtroy my ſelf, which had not divine power prevented, I had been a murderer of my own life, and of their lives that I loved moſt intirely, I have been waked in the night by the devill for this very purpoſe, and directed where to have the knife, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118503:6"/>what knife I ſhould take; &amp; theſe aſſaults followed me not ſeldom, but very often, which made my poor ſoul and body exceedingly to tremble; I was exceedingly hurried to duty, &amp; to Ordinances, ſo that I could not ſleep in my bed, &amp; was carried one while to draw forth a good condition from marks and ſigns, and if they were not in view, then my joy and comfort was gone, and my ſpirit was full of horror; love to the godly I thought had been an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible ſign to witneſs my good condition, and my thoughts much dwelt upon thoſe words, I <hi>Joh</hi> 3.14. <hi>We know that we have paſſed from death unto life, becauſe we love the brethren.</hi> Now then I came to examine my love, and to compare it to that love which was among the Saints, ſpoken of in Scripture, which was not a firſt evidence neither.</p>
            <p>This prop I was quite taken off from, I was now as a cripple, when his crutches are taken from him he falls; ſo my ſpirit was laid flat on the ground, and I was convinced that it was the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit alone that witneſſeth to the creature its good condition, and all witneſſes were nothing, if the Spirit did not witneſs: I was as if I had never heard of a Spirit, though I had profeſt much ſome years before; but becauſe I went about to eſtabliſh a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of my own, as it were by the works of the Law, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was left in the dark concerning the righteouſneſs of the Lord Jeſus, which I thought I had not denyed; and if any that were Goſpel enlightned Saints, had ſaid to me, you reſt in your good works, and expect to be ſaved ſome other way then alone by Jeſus Chriſt, I looked upon them as doing me great wrong, and ſpeaking very falſe, I thought, and I would ſay ſo to them, I am not ſo ignorant to look upon my works as any thing; but I was made to acknowledge afterward, that I had let up my own works in the room of Chriſt, and the Lord ſtript me at laſt of all gifts and inlargements in duty, and I was ſtriken dumb, or elſe faſt aſleep, when I have ſet my ſelf to pray, and it was indeed ſelf that the Lord ſtruck dumb, though I then beheld it not, but was ſore wounded, being perſwaded that I was for ever ſhut out from the preſence of God, which weight I could hardly bear, it was ſo burdenſom, that I ſtill cryed out, what ſhall I do? and all my prayer that was left me was this, <hi>Give me Chriſt, or elſe I die.</hi> Now nothing but a Chriſt would ſerve my turn, before it I could
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118503:7"/>have had tears or any relentings for ſin, or inlargements in duty, I was well enough, but the onely wiſe God knew it was beſt for me to be deprived of theſe which I ſo much builded upon and made idols of; I was as much troubled as <hi>Micah</hi> was, when Iſrael carried away his God.</p>
            <p>I am perſwaded that bare Profeſſors are the greateſt Papiſts in the world; ſpirituall idolatry is the worſt; and my experience teacheth me, that one may be a great worſhipper of Idols, and yet never bow down to a picture: But oh when the Lord took away my gods, how I lamented! and the more ſpirituall my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany was in their diſcourſe, the more ſtony hearted I was; I could freely ſpeak to thoſe that lived under an old adminiſtration, my ſpirit being under the ſame, a legall diſcourſe ſuited beſt with me; when I have been among thoſe that have been filled with joy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proffeſſors of Divine love, and much acquainted with free grace in the power of it, which I was very ignorant of, ſo that their company was burdenſom to me, yet I could not keep from them; ſometimes I have gone from them full of horror, and my heart ready to burſt, and my countenance hath ſtartled them that have come to viſit me; they have ſaid I looked ſo gaſtly, that they were affrighted to ſee me, asking me what I ailed, which I could hardly tell them, I was ſo filled the with terrors of the Law; I have come from hearing the word preached even diſtracted, ſo that my mother would ſay to me, if thou doſt faſt ſo day after day, and run thus up and down, the devill will take advantage againſt thee; but I could not indure to be ſpoken to, my ſpirit was ſo peeviſh and f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oward, and I apprehended I was never the better for my hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much, and praying and faſting, yet I could not forbear.</p>
            <p>And many that were inlightned in the doctrine of free grace, took a great deal of pains with me; perſwading me to hear thoſe Miniſters that taught moſt upon the doctrine of free grace, but I could not reliſh that doctrine, it was ſuch a cold, lean, poor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, I thought; I being under the flaſhes of hell, I delighted in the thunderings of the Law, and they pleaſed me beſt that preached moſt upon the Law, and that preſt legall qualifications, which I ſtrove to come up to, and thought I ſhould never have Chriſt without I was ſo qualified, as I was taught, unto which I could not attain, for all my ſtrugling and ſtriving after it, which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118503:7"/>made me conclude that I was not elected, if I were, I ſhould be made conformable to his Image, who is holy which I was not, and therefore I was none of Chriſts flock, which condition was very dreadful to me to be without Chriſt; and I could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a word of ſatisfaction from any, though ſome would ſay to me, doſt thou not love Chriſt? I would ſay, but how ſhall I know whether my love be true love? I may think I love Chriſt, and deceive my ſelf, I not being able to judge of may love, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were right or no; and therefore I was ſo puzled, becauſe I looked for that in the firſt place, which ſhould come in as a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond evidence, which cauſed my ſpirit continually to be in a hurry: I delighted to hear much of Chriſt preached to righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teou ones, but I cared not to hear Chriſt preached to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for I looked firſt for holineſs, and then for Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But the great and glorious God at length throughly convinced me of his juſtifying ungodly ones, and that he ſent Chriſt not to call the Righteous, but Sinners, and he came to ſave the chiefeſt of ſinners; and now I began to hearken to free grace, and I ſaw no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe could revive me, and I found my ſpirits a little ſtayed, in liſtening to the free tenders of Chriſt, and then I was put upon arguing with God, intreating him to give me Chriſt, which he had given as the onely object for poor ſinners to flie unto, being ſtung with ſin, he was the brazen Serpent that the father ſet up for to heal, and take away that ſting of ſin; and now, though I could not come unto God as a righteous one, I could come as a ſinner, and beg of God to receive me, being ſuch an object that he ſent forth his love to, commending it to ſinners, and to rebels; and I deſired, oh that I might be one of thoſe rebels that might have a pardon, were it upon never ſo hard terms; and truly I ſound God trying me to purpoſe: it was a very hard thing to me to be ranked amongſt the vildeſt miſcreants in the world, and to behold my ſelf as bad as the greateſt adulterer or blaſphemer in the world, which I looked upon to be a great deal vilder then I, and further from Gods accepting; but this conceit, free grace laid in the duſt, and Divine light ſhewed me the ſpawn and ſeed of all ſin within my corrupt nature, which made me to lie in the duſt, and to cry out, Lord let free grace own me, elſe I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done; when the Law of the Spirit came, then ſin revived, and I died; it ſhewed me every ſecret ſin that I ſaw not before,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118503:8"/>ſo that all my ſins were ſet in order before me, and I beheld them innumerable; Oh what a deplored condition was I i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forlorn and without hope, nothing now could comfort me but the true Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, and nothing could ſpeak peace to my ſoul but Chriſt; I ſaw I was undone, without the Son looked upon me, and my ſpirit grew very reſtleſs, and my thirſt was very great: oh how I long after the water of life! I often told God, I c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld not ſubſiſt without it, a generall promiſe would not ſerve my turn; though it a little quiteted me when I was in great agonies, yet I could not be ſatisfied without a knowledge of God as my father; I thought to hear of an inheritance, and not to have an intereſt in it, it did but aggravate my ſorrow, I muſt have a particular promiſe, the Spirit alſo to bear witneſs to my ſpirit, and ſealing me up to the day of Redemption; I muſt have an aſſurance upon good grounds, my heart could not now cheat me with a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit aſſurance, it had ſo often deceived me, and made me take comfort from falſe grounds, and ſtill carried me about, but never brought me to my journeys end, I entered not into my true reſt till the Lord brought me to ceaſe from my own works, and to take a Chriſt upon his own terms; Oh what a knotty piece was I for the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> to work upon! untill he put forth his mighty power, I could not believe; though many that cryed down free grace as a doctrine of liberty to ſin, I found no do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſo ſtriking at my ſins as it, and though ſome would tell me I had found out an eaſie way to heaven now, to go to heaven in believing, but I found it a hard way, yea, impoſſible, for I could not believe till the day of Gods power; I found it as eaſie to keep the whole Law, as to believe; I ſaw it alone the work of the moſt high, and in his own time his arm brought ſalvation to the heart of a poor miſerable loſt creature; had it not been for free grace, which I muſt continually acknowledge, and aſcribe praiſe to him, who is worthy of honour for evermore.</p>
            <p>I could ſpeak much concerning the time of my ſorrow, of my terrors and perplexities, and ſore plunges, I could make a large rehearſall, I could tell you much of the ſad apprehenſions I had of my eternall condition, which I have but as it were given you a little hint of, my condition in the time of my bonds, but my deſire now is rather to tell you of my freedom, unto which I haſten;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118503:8"/>though I know that theſe mourning experiences may be of great uſe to the ſorrowfull and troubled ſpirit, that lyeth languiſhing for want of the light of aſſurance, which God doth ſee good for a time to conceal from his beloveds, that he hath loved with an eternall love, which in time be draweth with loving kindneſs; Therfore let not any poor ſoul deſpair, there is free grace enough, an ocean, to ſwallow up, not my ſins onely, but many more, a fountain open for all manner of ſins, be they never ſo great: poor ſouls! you cannot out-ſin mercy, your ſins are finite, but grace is infinite; do not think that any ſin can ſhut thee out of divine love, if it could, it would have ſhut me out, for certain I am, that no heart could be more deſperatly wicked then mine, no ones ſins could be of a more ſcarlet dye then mine, ſtrong unbelief, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually departing from the living God, as full of heart hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie as I could hold; Oh let ſinners admire free grace with me, that hath freed me from as ſtony, as ſeared, benummed, ſenſleſs a condition, as any could or can be in; hearing or reading, or Saints ſpeaking to me, was as to one deaf; I ſtill concluded my condition to be like theirs the Scripture ſpeaks of, that were given up by the Lord to blindneſs of mind, and hardneſs of heart; I thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently God had given me to know that I ſhould periſh for ever, but Gods thoughts at length appeared higher then mine, as the Heavens are higher then the Earth; and when my Spirit had thus been upon the rack for a ſeaſon, and toſſed up and down with the waves of a continual accuſing troubled conſcience; And none ſpake any word that did in the leaſt meaſure revive me, till that voice ſounded that I could not contradict, but I did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, and repulſe it as long as I could, and when it ſpake as a ſtil ſmall voice, I rejected it a week, before I felt, heard and ſaw that glorious light and power, ſounded into my ſpirit, which cauſed an eccho, or anſwer from my ſpirit in believing the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Spirit, but that ſmall voice made ſuch a report in my ſoul, which made me to liſten; it was ſuch a ſpeaking that I had not heard before, therefore it was very ſtrange to me; the word I had was this, <hi>Chriſt is thine, and thou art his;</hi> and no word was ſpoken to my ſpirit for ſix or ſeven days but this; it followed me where ever I went; ſometimes as I have been going along the ſtreets, I have looked behind me, thinking I had heard ſome
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118503:9"/>locall voice, a voice without me, but ſure it was becauſe I was unacquainted with the voice of the Spirit ſpeaking in, or to the ſoul; I oft-times turned back when I have been going along the ſtreets, to ſee who it was that ſpake, taking that for viſible which was inviſible; I did not know that I had read ſuch a word in the Scripture, that the Spirit ſpake to me; but before my heart was brought over to believing the ſame power that raiſed Chriſt from the grave, appeared in deſtroying that ſtrong unbelief, that made me depart from the living God; and as in the fulneſs of time, Almighty power brought Chriſt into the world, and into the grave, it raiſed Chriſt alſo out of the grave; this ſame power was a hand by Divine appointment, leading me through varieties of inward bitter deſolations, untill it brought me not onely to the gates, but into a heaven of ſweet conſolation.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall by the aſſiſtance of the Spirit, tell the time when my heart was brought to believe the pardon of my ſins paſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and to come, by an act of grave through the blood of the Lord Jeſus, which I clearly ſaw by the light of the Spirit, bearing witneſs to my Spirit, that Chriſt was mine, and I was his.</p>
            <p>The time, the year 1642. the day, the firſt of the firſt moneth, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>January,</hi> it being the firſt day of the week, commonly called the Sabbath day, which was indeed a Lords day to my ſoul.</p>
            <p>While Mr. <hi>John Simpſon</hi> was preaching from that Scripture, in the 8 of the <hi>Romans,</hi> the words are theſe. <hi>Now if any man have not the ſpirit of Chriſt, be is none of his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many Sermons he preached from this Scripture, and he had ſhewed that the Spirit might be in that ſoul that was very dark, and much confuſed in its apprehenſions of Chriſt, as he proved from <hi>John</hi> 14.5, 6, 7. <hi>Thomas</hi> faith unto Chriſt, <hi>Lord we know not wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther thou goeſt, and how ſhould we know the way?</hi> Chriſt in the 4. <hi>verſe</hi> told them, they knew whither he went, and the way they knew, and he tells them that they had known the Father and ſeen him, and yet they ſaid they knew not; ſo that the Diſciples of Chriſt had ſometimes a confuſed knowledge of the Father and yet they had both ſeen and known; ſo that from thence was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that many poor ſouls might have the Spirit, as was inſtanced in many particulars; that the Spirit might be in the ſoul, though
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118503:9"/>it could not make it out, through that exceeding hurry the ſoul lay in, being ſtill in a confuſion, its darkneſs being not diſpelled by the glorious manifeſtation of the light of the ſpirit, ſealing it up to the day of Redemption.</p>
            <p>My Spirit was under much trembling, for fear it ſhould ſtill be ſaid that I had none of the Spirit, which often was a terrible ſound within me, which I ſtill dreaded, and my ſpirit cryed out to the Lord; when this Sermon before mentioned upon that 8. of the <hi>Romans</hi> was almoſt ended, I ſaid, Lord I have the Spirit, in this confuſed manner as I found a witneſs within me that I had the Spirit in thoſe particulars that were declared, but my ſpirit ſtrongly run out to the Lord for a clear manifeſtation of his love in Chriſt, and ſuddenly my ſoul was filled with joy unſpeakable, and full of glory in believing, the ſpirit witneſſing in that word, Chriſt is thy wel-beloved, and thou art his; my ſoul was now full of joy as it could hold, now I ſaw all my ſins laid upon Jeſus Chriſt, and when he was ſacrificed, all my ſins were ſacrificed with him; oh what triumphing and ſongs of <hi>Hallelujah</hi> were in my ſpirit, I knew not where I was, nor how to get out of the place where I ſat, I apprehended nothing but a clothing of glory over my whole man; I never beheld Saints as I did then, I ſaw their faces like the face of Angels; Oh what Angelicall creatures did they appear before me, full of ſhining brightneſs! oh what a heart inflamed now was mine, filled with the flame of Divine love! there appeared now no ſmoak, but a clear flame, nothing now before me but chriſtal appearances: oh how my ſoul was enamoured with Chriſt! Earth was now gone, and heaven come; the unclean ſpirit diſpoſſeſſed, the pure ſpirit now poſſeſt, taking my ſoul from the dunghill, and ſetting it upon the throne, my naturall food I taſted not till now, it was bitter to my taſte; but oh now, every bit of bread I eat, how ſweet was it to my taſte! Chriſt ſweetned every creature to me, oh how ſweet was the feaſtſ of love, that my ſoul was made partaker of in very creature! oh what a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound doth Divine love make in the ſoul! I could not keep love in, it would flame forth into a declaration, I muſt now tell Saints what I had now received from the ſpirits teſtimony, and that they might praiſe with me, having mourned with me; I told them I had now ſeen him whom my poor ſpirit doubted I ſhould never
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118503:10"/>have beheld, I called to others to come and taſte how ſweet and loving Chriſt is to ſinners; now Sermons appeared living to me; where Chriſt was preached moſt to ſinners, I delighted moſt in ſuch a Miniſtry, and ſtill went away with melody in my heart; for a whole year after, I was ſealed up to the day of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I had exceeding raptures of joy very frequent, little or no intermiſſions, no queſtions or doubtings in the leaſt meaſure, but my ſeat was ſtill for conſtancy, a ſeat of joy and ſpirituall mirth, though ſometimes the golden trumpet ſounded higher, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times lower, yet it ſtill was ſounding, and cauſed an eccho to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſore combat after the Spirits teſtimony.</head>
               <p>THe time of that glorious ſealing me, was after that teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in which my ſpirit was ſet at liberty, that day before mentioned, being the firſt day of the week, and year 1642. upon the third day of that week and year, my occaſions called me to <hi>Stepny,</hi> where I lodged at my Uncles all night, and my Aunt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up into the Chamber to me, ſhe ſaid to me, Coſen, the Lord hath taken your mother from you, now labour to be married to Chriſt, you have nothing to take up your time, but to labour for Chriſt; I anſwered, I hope I am married to Chriſt; but as ſoon as my Aunt was gone down ſtairs from me, the Lord ſpoke to me, and ſaid, I have made thee as ſure of ſalvation, as I am God in heaven; why didſt thou ſay thou hopeſt, and didſt not rather tell that thy God had aſſured thee that Chriſt was thine, thou having ſuch a clear teſtimony of the ſpirit, witneſſing with thy ſpirit in ſuch a bright light of glory, that thou couldſt not but aſſent to it, thou ſhouldſt now have declared it?</p>
               <p>Satan preſently was let looſe upon me, as ſoon as the Lord had ſpoken theſe words, which I am ſure was from the Lord, they came in ſuch Majeſty, that cauſed all my joints to tremble, and ſore perplexed I was; Satan buffetted, and my own heart ſtrongly ſet upon me, perſwading me that I had fallen from grace, and I had denied the Spirits work in me, and now I was nearer to periſhing then ever; very hideous thoughts I was filled with and nothing but blackneſs before me; now I had ſinned
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118503:10"/>againſt the ſpirit, and this was more dreadfull to me then all the time of my bondage, for I thought now the unclean ſpirit would have torn me a pieces, I was ſo terrified I could not go to bed till midnight, but walked about the chamber hearing nothing, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but damnation and hell ſet before me, I thought my tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be as great as any of the damned, wherein it was a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible hell to me for the time, which time, the indeared love of the Father ſuffered not to be long, it was not above three hours; my heavenly Father knew, had that extremity of ſpirit laſted long, it would have conſumed my vitall ſpirits, but as love moved my Father to ſpeak kindly to my diſtreſſed ſpirit, in taking away this unexpreſſible torment, he gave me unexpreſſible glory and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing; And when I gave up all that I had received for loſt at the very nick of time, and this night that was ſo dreadful to me, before the morning light my ſpirit was full of light, and a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhining light then I ſaw before, I now beheld; And the ſpirit ſpeaking that word in great power, Chriſt is thine, and thou art his, and the gates of hell ſhall never prevail againſt thee, all the power and policy of the devil ſhall not hurt thee, ſo as to deprive thee of thy Saviour. I had the repreſentation of a ſeal ſet upon the wax, the ſpirit as fire made my ſtony ſpirits pliable for it to leave its mark or impreſſion and ſtamp was ſet on my ſpirit, now I felt, ſaw and heard, that I never did before: oh that A<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ras of glory, that now was my clothing! now was I made like my Saviour, a crown given me, not made with pearls or rich diamonds, but far richer, not to be valued; earth cannot wear this crown, its onely the heaven of God that muſt injoy this preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, its thoſe that are made Kings and Prieſts unto God, that are thus honoured; oh how tranſcendently glorious is the true ſealing of the Spirit! ſure no tongue is able to ſpeak it out, the pen of the readieſt writer cannot write this, it may give ſome hints of this ſeal, but for depth, length, and breadth, who can give a full deſcription or relation of it, it is a thing impoſſible to be publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Oh then you ſealed ones, come admire with me, who can tell forth <hi>Sions</hi> glory? Could not <hi>Paul</hi> tell what he ſaw in the third heavens? How then ſhall we declare our heavens glory, when we know not whether we are in the body or out? Our joy is ſuch, when the ſpirit takes us up, we know not where we are, for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118503:11"/>that preſent, though afterward it may be we are found in the Iſle of <hi>Pathmos,</hi> our bodies may be found amongſt the <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> yea, and our ſpirits too, our communion taken away, but not our union; no doubting or queſtioning concerning that, though there may be much diſſertion and darkneſs, as I ſhall tell you God willing, he giving me life to accompliſh my deſire, which is to leave the Saints a Legacy of experiences, that they may read, not my works, but the ſpirits works, and ſo admire him who is moſt worthy, when I am gone hence, and ſhall be no more ſeen.</p>
               <p>And if I vary concerning ſome experiences in this, in reſpect of doubting, and queſtioning union after ſealing, it is my own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, I muſt not record anothers experience; it may be ſome may ſcruple at it, and therefore I thought fit to mention it.</p>
               <p>After my Spirit received the ſeal of the Spirit, I had abundance of raptures of joy, ſome when I have gon along the ſtreet, my rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures hath been ſuch, that I minded not the ground I went upon, but divers times have been ready to fall flat on the plain ground; I have had ſometimes ſo great raviſhing of ſpirit, when I have been alone in a room by my ſelf, my outward man hath been ſo altered on a ſudden, to the view of thoſe that have been in the houſe, which have found me alone, and not able to ſpeak to them for a ſeaſon, ſo that they have been frighted, thinking me not to be in health; and they beholding the tears falling from my eyes, have wondred what I ailed; but it was becauſe the Son of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſhone hot upon my ſpirit, which cauſed a melting into tears, and many Scriptures opened to me, which I ſpoke to them that ſat by, which have been aſtoniſhed to hear and ſee a poor creature ſo filled, but it was Chriſt in me making uſe of me to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the excellency of Jeſus Chriſt, which my ſoul was ſo enamour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with; that my old Aunt ſitting by me, ſaid, ſhe had lived above threeſcore years, and yet never felt ſuch joy of the ſpirit, and yet a very godly woman; ſhe wept to ſee me ſo, her heart was much affected. And this year in which I was new-born, I ſhall (the Lord helping me) give forth ſome few of thoſe diſcoveries, which whole volumes cannot contain; Let free grace have all the glory.</p>
               <p>Oh to be in Chriſt! who can tell out his or her eſtate, night and day? How pleaſant is it? Such a one where ever it goes, cannot
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118503:11"/>but ſet forth its beloved, it cannot tell how to ſpeak of any thing elſe but Chriſt, it cannot tarry there where it may not ſpeak of its Saviour; no language is pleaſant to it, but that wherein its God is exalted; oh how ſweet was my ſleeping and waking, ſtill I had reſt in the boſom o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jeſus, oh what a great delight I had to be amongſt the Saints, and my heart was full of zeal for his glory? oh what an eagerneſs and forwardneſs there is to receive good, and to do good in that time of the ſouls firſt converſion! then its forward to ſuffer any thing for Chriſt; nick names are nothing to it, ſcandals and reproaches it can trample under foot; but when the doctrine of free grace was nick-named, as ſome would tell me it was a doctrine of liberty to ſin, then I could not but ſpeak ſharply to ſuch; I found no doctrine leading to holineſs ſo much as it, no ſalve drawing out corruptions and ill humors like this, no plaiſter healing the moſt deſperate wound, like the plaiſter of free grace; its cleanſing phyſick, it runneth between the marrow and the bones; ſinners, would you be rid of bloody ſins! Free grace hath opened a fountain for to waſh in, not onely your feet, but head and hands, yea your whole man; in this fountain I was cleanſed, by this wine my drooping ſpirits were revived, Chriſt was that good <hi>Samaritan,</hi> that found me wounded, whom the Law nor Prieſt did not pitty; legall threatnings, and legall promiſes looked upon me, but piſſed by and left me wallowing in blood, and pained with wounds; and if it had not been for that tender hearted <hi>Samaritan</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, I had periſhed; oh how comfortable was his oyl and wine to my wounds! great was his care for me, no tender mother like to Jeſus; the Saints told me when I mourned for the loſs of my tender mother, that Chriſt would be more tender, and would be all to me in the loſs of earthly comforts; and he was more to me then they told me, he was double comfort, and a Comforter that hath tarried and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with me, and will abide with me for ever, a Comforter that was ſtill revealing love, and bringing love tokens to my ſoul, and ſetting before me varieties of diſhes at every bankquet, for a year together, my meat was ſweet meats from heaven, my drink wine upon the lees, wines well refined, milk and hony was my or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary diſh, the leaſt appearance of God was marvellous ſweet ſome days and nights I had feaſts full of marrow, and viſious full of glory.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118503:12"/>
               <p>In the night before ſleep had ſeized upon me, a bright light ſhined round my head viſible and in the midſt of that light ſtood one all in white, in the likeneſs of a creature all covered with brightneſs, my outward man at this light was ſtricken very weak, and all in a ſweat but I received much joy, and was bid by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpeaking of the ſpirit not to fear, for I had ſeen an Angell; ſurely it was a very glorious viſion, ſuch a perfume was left in my ſpirits all that night, and my ſtrength of body given me as ſoon as this viſion was ended, and I was full of triumphing in the Lord, who killeth and maketh alive; oh how ſweet are true viſions! oh that I could praiſe more that God that hath, is, and will be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to me for ever! my ſong was when the ſentence of death was on my earthly Tabernacle, by reaſon of illneſs I ſtill was filled with this joyfull long; Oh death where is thy ſting? Oh grave vvhere is thy victory? Death vvas ſtill preſenced vvithout a ſting, and the Lavv vvithout ſtrength, theſe vvere novv diſſolved and gone, and I ſavv an accompliſhment of the great vvork of Redemption by Jeſus Chriſt; I could not but dance before this Ark, though <hi>Michols</hi> mocked; I muſt declare that I was paſt from Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> into the Regions of Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> where I ſaw an end of the Law for Righteouſneſs ſake to every one that believes; not that I was now without Law unto God, neither deſpiſed I any part of the Law, but beheld it good, if a man or woman uſe it lawfully, the Apoſtle could not have ſaid the Law had been faulty as in the Hebrews: But in reſpect of our corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in the uſing of it, we it were that were faulty, not the Law in it ſelf, that was pure, but I looked not where I might not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee it in its purity without me, but enjoy it within me, which while I looked firſt on commands and then on promiſes, I could not attain to it; but when I beheld firſt promiſes, and then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, novv I ſavv an attaining to the Lavv of righteouſneſs, though not in or by my ſelf, yet in and by another; novv I look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Lavv and legall precepts vvith an Evangelicall eye, vvhereas before the light of the ſpirit cam<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, I turned Goſpel into Lavv, but novv appeared a harmony betvveen both; a Lavv within me, not making void that vvithout me, but novv vvas given me a help meet, in behold<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng morall precepts in Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call arms, <hi>Sinai's</hi> voice in <hi>Sions</hi> breaſt, novv frovvns are gone,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118503:12"/>and ſimiles are come, thunder is fallen, and the ſtill voice is riſen, death under, life in the top, which crown ſin nor Satan can never deprive Saints of, for Saints are not under legall precepts, but under Goſpel commands, and in this ſenſe they are dead to the Law by the life or Chriſt in them.</p>
               <p>And for this tenent of truth, I paſſed under the name of Anino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian, but praiſed be the Lord, I was not one by adherency, though by imputation; Antinomianiſm was not inherent in me, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to by me, this name in plain terms is liberty to ſin; as the Divel nick names Saints, ſo he nick names the doctrine of grace too, and ſin which is like himſelf, he puts upon is a nick-name garment, greater is he that is within Saints, then he that is in the world, Saints garment is Jeſus Chriſt, and nothing can rear or rent, or defile this garment; Saints clothing is the pureſt white, no dirt throwed upon it can ſoil it; oh Saints rejoyce with me; ſhall we be found wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to enter in at the ſtraight gate, and plucked into the houſe by the hand of the Angell of the new Covenant, when they without ſhall be ſtricken with blindneſs, and ſo not able to find he door? Why muſt a <hi>Zoar</hi> be preſerved for us, and a <hi>Sodom</hi> ſet on fire? Why muſt ſome be veſſels of diſhonour, and ſome of honour, ſome that are high-wayes, and lyers about in the hedges, fetched in to ſup with Chriſt, and the grave ones of the world muſt not ſo much as have a taſte of Chriſts dainties? F<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee grace, and nothing but free grace makes us to differ from others; oh let the redeemed of the Lord ſay ſo, let not <hi>Sion</hi> boaſt of her own righteouſneſs, which ſhe hath done, but let her look by whom ſhe hath her dignity, who ſtrikes off all ſelf-boaſting; the more free grace is apprehended, the more ſelf-righteouſneſs is reprehended, the creature can never learn the leſſon of humiliation and ſelf-denial, till it hath been in the School of free grace, that is, the free School where the beſt learning is to be had, the poor and fatherleſs here find mercy; and here the Governor of this Free-ſchool receiveth every poor Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, he refuſeth none that comes, though they have not one friend to make ſuit for them; nay, ſuch are ſoon entertained that truſt wholly to this great Governors mercy, they have the beſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, here is no reſpect of perſons, but the poor begger that lyeth in the ſtreet, that knows not where to have a bit of bread, lath nothing but a clothing of tatters, to outward view a very miſerable creature,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118503:13"/>ſuch a one more reſpected then a rich <hi>Dives</hi> that goeth in his vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet and diadems of gold very day; oh what manner of love is this! that makes no difference between fools and learned ones, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ideots before the wiſdom of the world, making the ignorant and erring Spirit to have the greateſt underſtanding? Surely ſuch muſt needs magnifie free grace; oh how low is that creature in its own eyes, that lives in the ſpirit, and fetcheth nothing from its own free will, or from any work of his own, but all from Chriſt he ſticks no flower in his boſom, but that which none can ſnatch from him; his walks of delight, is in no garden but where he may ſee his beloved walk before him; the Saint that is throughly ſpiritual, loves dearly to walk incloſed in the arms of its Saviour, and to be imbraced by him, and kiſſed with the kiſſes of his mouth, for his love is better then wine; the ſpirits of wine hath a great efficacy in quickning thoſe that faint and ſound away, but of a ſtronger efficacy is divine love, it makes dead ſouls live, yea, though they are as a tree twice dead and plucked up by the roots, dead once, and plucked up, and ſet again and again, and pruned and dunged, and it becomes wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, dead; though ſin hath killed the ſoul, ſo as to make it wither, no convictions, no legall promiſes, thoſe are ſuch promiſes that are made with conditions, no ſuch ſtriving can fetch life into one dead in ſin and treſpaſſes; all ſtrugling and ſtriving in this caſe, is but like the pains which the gardner takes with dead plants, that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his skill to recover, but what the skill of the Gardner cannot reach, Divine love can; the dead withered ſoul, though to its own view, and to others view it appear irrecoverable, Divine love lifts this dead ſoul, though it hath lain in the grave of ſin, that in the thoughts of others, its quite putrified, as they thought of <hi>Lazarus</hi> body: Let not dead ſouls be diſcouraged, for there is life enough for them, when not appehended by them; once my note was nothing but ſorrowful complaining of a dead, ſeared, ſtony, hard heart, a Spirit I though: nothing could have ſtuck upon it, or have ſoaked into ſuch a heart ſo hard; as it was often my expreſſion, my heart no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can poſſible enter it, for it is as hard ſurely, as the neather mil-ſtone, I could not tell what to liken it to, I thought it harder then any thing; yet though it was very hard, melting love wrought upon it.</p>
               <p>Now I wrought from life, and not for it, the ſpirit makes every
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118503:13"/>duty a pleaſure, whereas I ſorely tugged to get up my heart in a duty, when I looked upon it as a task which I muſt do, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide ſtraw too, it was a burden I greatly groaned under; when I was put upon duties by a command, and I had no frame of ſpirit ſuitable, nor no words, I had nothing to fulfill my task, and yet I was preſt to do it, or elſe the threatning reached me, and terrified; but when my Mediator came, he overcame all my enemies that kept me under, and ſhewed them to me dead and drowned in that red Sea, his blood, which victory was a long time accompliſhed, before I ſaw it; but when Chriſt made known to me my freedom, bringing me out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> then I offered ſacrifices without interruption; now I had that brought to hand, which wrought all in me, and for me; when duty is accompanied with priviledge, there is then a delight in duties; I was mightily taken with priviledge, and it was meat and drink to me to be much in hearing, praying and meditating, and converſing, and I could do little elſe for a year; I now met with God in duties, I made them not my Comforters, but Chriſt in them, and as they were priviledges given me by him, ſo I enjoyed them, giving Chriſt the preheminence, which was due to him, I having all from the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not of debt, but by gift; thoſe that ſay they enjoy all from him, they give all to him, and rejoice in him, as their onely Portion.</p>
               <p>My Dear boſom friends, with whom I have fellowſhip in the ſpirit, from that ingagement of love that is upon me, I am ſtrongly moved to declare to you the ſundry dealings of God with me, the time of bondage, and freedom from that bondage, hath been declared, though but in ſhort; Now after this hot Sun ſhine, there aroſe a black cloud, which appeared ſmall at the firſt riſing, but it ſtill ſpread bigger and bigger, till it filled the heavens with black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the heaven in which God had ſet up his throne, in which the King of glory took delight, which is the Saints, this heaven was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with clouds, and this dark cloud had its firſt riſing out of the Sea, which Sea in its ſelf, when not troubled, its very clam and ſmooth, and to ſwim upon it there is no danger: if we keep in the ſhip we are ſafe, but when winds ariſe, this calm Sea is troubled, contrary winds makes the ſmooth Sea full of waves and billows, and it becomes very tempeſtuous, and the creature is put to ſome plunges, and toſſed up and down, though in the ſhip, yet many are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118503:14"/>put to great ſtraits, by reaſon of ſuch mighty ſtorms which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a-men meet withall, yet valiant Sea-mens hearts do not ſink without a leak be ſprung in the ſhip, then their hearts ake, and the ſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt ſpirits then begin to dye: but as long as the ſhip is firm, the coragious Marryner doth not fear; there is no danger ſo long as they keep the Sea under them and out of them, it will never drown them, but prove a ſweet refreſher. Oh what pleaſure doth the Marryners take, when they get the maſtery over the ſtorm, and not it over them.</p>
               <p>This Sea in which my ſpirit firſt received trouble and dark diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, began to take hold of my rejoycing ſpirit; it was an eager preſſing after the way of worſhip, to know the right way, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it. I earneſtly ſought for, but could not find; now there aroſe contrary winds, which did blow ſo ſtrong, that this ſmooth and pleaſant Sea began to be ſo full of waves, and ſtorms grew ſo faſt, that my joy ſunk, there grew a thick skin over my ſight of union, and truly I minded not that which was my life, ſo much as the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a way of worſhip, which night and day I lay poring upon, I could not take my natural reſt, my thoughts dwelt ſo continually upon the ſtudy of Ordinances, and the right adminiſtrations, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that practice in the time of the Apoſtles, the which I could not find any come up unto; fain I would have been in the practice of all the Ordinances that Chriſt left his Diſciples to be helps meet to them, and I believe they are a Sea on which Saints may ſwim ſafely, till they arrive at their haven of eternal glory; Saints voyage continues till their mortal ſhall put on immortality, and till then, the waters are for Saints to float upon. Saints you are a float, keep in your Ark and you are ſafe, take heed of the bluſtring winds, which is too much eagerneſs, extrams will toſs your ſpirits, they may drown your comfort and joy of union, though nothing can poſſibly drown your union. Saints you have need to ſtand upon your watch Tower, even at the time when you are ſeeking after ſpiritual things, for we have within us ſuch a corrupt ſpirit, which proves ſuch a treacherous enemy, it betrayes us into the hands of Satan, which is that roaring Lion that goeth about, ſeeking whom he may devour, and ſo joyneth with our enemy within us, to fight againſt us.</p>
               <p>Therefore unto all the Saints that practice, as they think, all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances that Chriſt left to his Diſciples, I ſhall ſpeak this word to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118503:14"/>you, have a care your fall not overhead and ears into this Sea; If you keep upon it, it may be very ſweet to you, but if it once flow over your ſpirits you ſink; my meaning is this, if any thing below Chriſt, yea, though it be an inſtitution of Chriſt, if thou exalts it higher then thou ſhouldſt, thou diſhonoureſt Chriſt, and indangers thy ſpirituall welfare, truly Saints are very apt to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place things: every thing may be uſefully kept in their right ſphear, but when that which ſhould be beneath gets uppermoſt, then comes in confuſion and darkneſs; for it we rejoyce more in the Adminiſtration then in the Adminiſtrator, dark miſty clouds will ariſe upon our ſpirits, and if a ſecond vail cover our ſight, it is worſe for us then when the Law was a vail. Obſcurity after the ſhining of Goſpel light is terriblyer to bear, then that darkneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a freedom, for when once the ſoul hath a freedom from le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall bondage by the ſpirit, that it can cry <hi>Abba</hi> father, and have Communion in the ſight of union with God, as their father; and now though union may be in ſight, yet it is afar off, and for want to Communion, the poor ſoul cannot take the felicity in its union, as it ſhould; And truly, if we have too high eſteem of things, we ſhall enthrall our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Therefore dear friends, let God be your all, and not Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; let God be your all, and not any practice, though a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice preſcribed by the ſpirit; its a dangerous thing to have our thoughts too much upon or after things, we are ſo apt to make that our all, our hearts are ſo ready to delude us, when our eye is a little off Chriſt; therefore let us ſtill deſire a fixed eye upon God in Chriſt, for this is the ſafeſt Road, there is no damage to that ſoul that continually keeps his feaſts with Chriſt, for Chriſt is at all the coſt: Oh that Saints were more in ſpiritual practice! the Lord knoweth I would not undervalue, or have a ſlight thought of of any Adminiſtration, or of any Saint, for ſurely I prize them; but the ſum of all my ſpeaking is; to give God his due, and by him we ſhall be thought to give every thing its due, and in ſo doing, how ſweet will our harmony be; and though we be at a loſs in reſpect of externa<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, yet that ſweet internal converſe will delight our ſpirits, if that be not ſmothered by ſin and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, which aims to give that a greater blow then any thing elſe; and this blow my ſpirits felt; it was not externals that cauſed my
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118503:15"/>diſſertion, for they are good in themſelves; I would not be thought to make them the cauſe or put fault in them, the fault was in my ſelf; concerning Ordinances, I ſtill went on trying and examining the way which ſundry Congregations walked in, and I walked a moneth or there abouts with one Congregation, and a time with another, and ſo with divers people I tryed their way; but I could not be ſatisfied in my ſeeking, becauſe I found not, neither was I taken off from that reſtleſs frame I was in, till a conſtant over powring word came, which was this: I ſay to thee wait, it is the mind of thy God that thou ſhouldſt wait; then my ſpirit was quiet, and I clearly underſtood that it was the mind of God not to diſcover a way of worſhip to me, in that I could not behold the practice of any people under any form, to be like the pattern in mount <hi>Sion;</hi> I could not apprehend their practice to be like that of old time, which the Scripture makes mention of, which was a practice full of the ſpirit, and the gifts of the ſpirit they had not onely a letter, but the ſpirit bear witneſs to their practice, they were full of the ſpirit, of love and unity; not judging and ready to cenſure thoſe that were not under the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation as they were, they loved Saints as Saints, and oh that Saints were in ſuch a frame as to eye Saintſhip more, and to love one another, becauſe of that heavenly relation they are in, having one Father and one Saviour!</p>
               <p>I onely briefly mention ſome things concerning the time of my ſpirits firſt ſtep into diſſertion, and I cannot but warn Chriſts babes, nay, though they be young men; that is ſuch as are grown from their time of infancy to riper years, yet; thoſe that are more ſtrong in the faith, that have got higher then an Infant in ſpirituality, even theſe may be cautioned to take heed that they look not more upon externals, then upon internals: Saints, fetch all your comforts from your Saviours boſom, ſtill eye that which is from everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to everlaſting, its a very ſecure centering in Jeſus; we are ſtill in hazzard of loſing our ſpirits when they take a rambling from Mountains to Hills, ſometimes they fall into a deep valley ere they are aware, and when they are down, many again find it a long time ere they can get up.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118503:15"/>
            <p>HItherto you have had an account of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of God with her, from the beginning of his Works in her, in various diſpenſations of Free-Grace, through Light and Darkneſs, Liberty and Bondage; wherein the deep and more diſcerning Generation of Chriſtians may diſcover the beginnings and growing up of the child Jeſus in her, unto greater meaſures of Wiſdom and Power then are common to moſt Saints: and withall, ſome hints from God of the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of his will, to magnifie the Wonders and Powers of his Spirit by her, in ſome notable and tranſcending way; where God begins to break down the Walls of fleſh in a Creature, in ſuch a rending way, upon thoſe ruines he raiſeth up a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Heaven and of Glory to be admired; In the deeps do men behold the wonders of the Lord; and be lays the foundation of his Chambers in the depths. Here followeth a Relation how the Glory of God appeared in her, in a time of ſore ſickneſs, when to all appearance ſhe was nigh unto death ſhewing the precious and Powerfull faith that wrought in her, and the mighty witneſs of God to the truth of her faith in a Glorious Effect of his Power demonſtrated upon her in a viſible way; whereby god would ſeem as by a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Sign to manifeſt that the Inviſible God dwells in her, and would put to ſilence the Ignorance, Pride, and Rage of fleſh againſt the Preſence and Power of God in her: And whereby ſhe ſeems to be ſet forth of God as an Example to all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118503:16"/>them that believe of a Faith and Power with God that is to be attained, beyond what moſt have yet received the enjoyment of; The Myſterie of Faith with Power in the heights and depths of it, being yet very little underſtood, and leſs enjoyed by the Lords deareſt Children; For whoſe ſake this is come forth at length after ſome years Concealment, and the rather in ſuch a day as this: wherein the Saints are called to put on again the Faith once delivered: whereby they overcame all things both within and without, and all things became ſubject unto them: The account hereof follows as it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to us in her own Words and Writings.</p>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:118503:16"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T being the deſire of all the Saints, and of all that wiſh well to <hi>Sion</hi> to hear of the experiences each of other, that they have in the pourings out of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which God hath ſaid he will pour out in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter days upon all fleſh; his Sons and his Daughters ſhall Propheſie, many promiſes we have in the like nature; And faith Chriſt, thoſe that believe as the Scripture hath ſaid, <hi>out of their belly ſhall flow Rivers of living Waters;</hi> this ſpake he of the Spirit which ſhould be given after his Aſcention to the Father; therefore the Saints are to expect it, and the more the Spirit ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, the greater will be the rage of Antichriſt; but the greater their Tribulations are, the nearer will be their time of deliverance; and Chriſt encourages Saints to liſt up their heads, for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption draweth nigh; And Chriſt tells believers it is not only given them to believe, but to ſuffer; and the Apoſtle bids us not think it ſtrange concerning fiery Tryals: for ſuch things we muſt meet withall before we enter into Glory, even that glory promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Saints in this life. Now Saints, the dropings and glimmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Spirit begin to appear, the day begins to dawn, the day-ſtar ſhall appear in its brightneſs, ſo that it ſhall be ſaid to the Saints, <hi>ariſe and ſhine, for your light is come, and the glory of the Lord is riſen upon you;</hi> then ſhall the Saints be of one mind, and one heart, and ſhall not need to teach one another; Saying, <hi>know the Lord, for they ſhall all be taught of God, from the leaſt to the greateſt, and then ſhall light break forth as at noon day;</hi> Surely, then believers ſhall be more frequent in calling to each other, to tell what God hath done for their ſouls, as I the moſt unworthy ſervant of the Lord Jeſus, am engaged to declare what God hath lately done for me, putting forth his Power, both for the remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the diſtemper from ſoul and body, which now I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the praiſe and glory of Free-Grace; And I doubt not but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118503:17"/>that it will be to the joy of all the Saints, for unto them I call to magnifie the Lord with me, and that we may exalt his name toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for it ſhould be the delight of Saints to ſet up God, and not ſelf, becauſe what they are or have is all by Grace, ſo that the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Not unto us, but unto thy name be the praiſe;</hi> this O friends! this makes me to abhor my ſelf in duſt and aſhes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have ſeen the Lord more then in an ordinary manner; So that I cannot but ſpeak the things which I have ſeen and heard from the holy Spirit, and this may be ſufficient to draw out your attentions, and ſerious conſiderations to that experience I am about to ſpeak through the ſtrength of the Spirit which bears wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to what I ſpeak to be truth, which Spirit ſhall lead into all truth. Saints, let me tell you, or the Spirit making uſe of me to tell you, that though a Cloud and Darkneſs may for a time cover your Spirits after you are Called, and Juſtified, and Sanctified by the holy Spirit in believing, for the Tryal of your faith which is much more precious then Gold or Silver, for certainly when God ſeems to be at a diſtance from the ſoul in reſpect of Communion, ſo that God ſeems to be afar off, and yet the ſoul made one Spirit with the Lord Jeſus; And this was my condition, that though I could own God as my Father, and had the Spirit of Adoption, whereby I could cry <hi>Abba,</hi> Father, and faith given to believe the pardon of all my ſins paſt, preſent, and to come, even then my Spirits were ready to crack in the apprehenſion of my ſelf the greateſt of ſinners, though brought up in the moſt ſtricteſt ways of God, according to that light, even from my Cradle, never given to any licentious ways, as I could ſay much to this purpoſe, when I came to look on God as a conſuming fire.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall forbear to ſet forth the dealings of God with me before and after Converſion, and in Converſion; which my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion was four years ago, wanting about a Quarter of a year, and for a year I may ſay I lived in the Regions of Heaven, being always rejoycing and prayſing God, but ſince that many Clouds of Darkneſs hath paſſed over my Spirits; But to ſpeak of the late deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God with me about half a year before my ſickneſs, my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits groaned after the pourings forth of the Spirit, that ſo there might be a greater perfection break forth in my words, thoughts and actions: The Word perfect did much ſeize upon my ſpirits, but the more I ſought for it, the further off (it went; to my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118503:17"/>God was at a diſtance from me, yet in the greateſt darkneſs I had the light of Union, but my ſoul breathed after Communion with my God, that though when I was among the Saints, Enlargements were given in; Yet when I was ſeparated from them, and thinking to have Communion with God alone, my mouth hath been ſtopped, and my ſpirits in a Priſon, not able to ſpeak to God, becauſe God ſpake not to me; For the Creature cannot ſpeak till God ſpeaks, <hi>but I ſtill thirſted, and my ſoul panted, as the Hart after the water brooks;</hi> And the nearer the time of light grew, the thicker I apprehended the Cloud; But praiſed be my Father that hath wrought a deliverance in me, for me, a ſtregthening of the Inward man, in decaying of the Outward (I cannot but ſay a) ſickneſs, but it was no more then a bodily weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and though a great weakneſs, and extream pain took hold of my body, all pain and diſtemper was removed from my ſpirits in a moment.</p>
               <p>The beginning of my diſtemper of body was about the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>June</hi> 1646. And from that time it waxed more and more upon me, but I ſtrove againſt it as long as I could, and went abroad till the latter end of the forenamed moneth; about the twenty eighth day I took my Chamber, the feveriſh diſtemper growing ſtill ſtronger; and the beginning of <hi>July,</hi> which is ſo called, on the firſt day of that moneth, which was the fourth day of the week in the morning, I had thoughts to go forth, thinking the Feaver had been wearing away, but on a ſuddain that morning a great extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of pain ſeized on my body, that as ſoon as I was out of my bed, I was fain to lye down again, and it was in much pains, and great heavineſs of ſpirit, and a rending of heart, ſo that I watered my Couch with my tears, and I lay very heavy in ſpirit all that day, and much pained in body, and by that time night came, my ſtrength of body was quite taken from me, ſo that I could not help my ſelf, but friends were fain to help me into bed, and aſſoon as I was laid, I felt the knot unknit, and the heavineſs of my ſpirits removed, and darkneſs expelled, and Sathan fled, and corruptions mortified, and all diſtempers of ſpirit disbanded, that now inſtead of a Chaos of Confuſion, a Fabrick of Glory was ſet before me; And my ſpirit was ſo drawn forth in a view of God, ſo much glory was preſented before me, ſuch Viſions of the Eternal God, that tongue is not able to expreſs; the Raptures were ſo great, that I
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118503:18"/>was not ſenſible of a body, whether in the body or out of the body God knows; But theſe diſcoveries were as coals of fire within me, which could not be kept in, and theſe pourings forth of love had in them ſuch a heat that it melted my frozen ſpirits, which cauſed my eyes to drop tears, that though in the morning my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits were rended, at evening <hi>the Son of Righteouſneſs aroſe with healing in his wings, and uttering his Voice,</hi> telling me he was my beloved that would not leave me, and thus renewing of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Evidences I had from Scripture, when the power of God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled me to believe for my free Juſtification in the Lord Jeſus, and alſo giving in immediately from himſelf in Scripture Language, as thus: I am thy father that hath pardoned thy iniquity for my own names ſake, and I will never remember thy ſins againſt thee any more, for I thy God change not, but reſt in my love, and rejoyce over thee with joy and ſinging, as it is written; And thus the Lord told me that though I had been as an untamed Heifer, like <hi>Ephraim</hi> in my thoughts and words; yet his bowels of love were not ſtraitned towards me, but he looked on me as one of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved ones in the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>This ſpeech from God came with a mighty luſtre beyond what I am able to expreſs, and that Scripture mixed with it, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14, <hi>I have healed thy back-ſlidings, and loved thee freely,</hi> and I lay not this weakneſs on thy body to upbraid thee, becauſe thou haſt lived ſo long in the fleſh, and walked ſo little in the ſpirit, but this weakneſs on thy body, is, that the power of thy God may be made manifeſt; And I ſaith the Lord wil teach and inſtruct thee, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, and reform thee by this my viſitation which is in my love to thee; and the Lord was pleaſed to tell me the reaſon why my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs took ſo little effect on the Saints, that it was because I did not tell them of their faults in a way of love, and in the meekneſs of my Saviour, and he ſweetly informed me, and told me for the future how I ſhould ſpeak to the Saints, and God <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lrried me out all the time of my ſickneſs to ſpeak ſuitable unto perſons, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to each conditions.</p>
               <p>And thus God came in the firſt night, the flood of Divine excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency ſhined down mightily, that ſome Saints ſtanding by me could not but conclude that certainly I was going out of the body, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ere long I ſhould be in enjoyment of what I ſaw expreſly flow from the Spirit, which to them it appeared ſo glorious, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118503:18"/>they were amazed that ſtood by me, and that night I ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſpeaking, or rather the ſpirit in me.</p>
               <p>And the next day I was deſirous to be out of the body, I longed to be diſſolved, and while I continued pleading with God to be out of the body, entreating to go hence, that ſo I might be ſwallowed up in glory, leſt continuing in the body, I ſhould act in the fleſh, and ſo diſhonour my loving father; and in the midſt of this and many other requeſts to God, this Scriprure was preſented, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6.2. which voice was from God, my thoughts not being on it, nor none ſpeaking of it but God alone; it came thus, after two daies I will revive thee, and the third day I will raiſe thee up, and thou ſhalt live in my ſight, and with a full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion that I ſhould recover; but I ſaid Lord, this Scripture holds out my reſurrection, or the reſtoring of the Jews, I was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered it was to manifeſt my recovery; but this departed from me, and the glory of God ſhined exceeding bright, and through the ſweet odour of the ſavour of the ſpirit, which Scripture com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares to ointment, which mightily drew out my love to my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and to the Saints, debaſing and loathing my ſelf, and my love was drawn out to the greateſt perſecutors of our times, I could have lain under their feet to have done them good; and many Scriptures were preſented, and a three-fold interpretation given on them; Scriptures never appeared ſo ſweet to me as they did then, and as many as the ſpirit brings to my remembrance, I ſhall relate.</p>
               <p>Further on the Lords day after, (ſo indeed it was to me a Lords day) in the fore-noon as I lay in the ſtrength of the fever, burning very much within, but without like a clod, and my ſtomack be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhut up, not able to take the creatures, nor to hear them ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, my ſtomack was ſo weak, that all that fortnight I lay and took nothing but ſmall beer, &amp; a little juice of cherries, or conſerve of currants, I took a little ſometimes for cooling of me, I did ſo burn in my throat and ſtomack; I remained thus like a dead car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe in reſpect of bodily ſtrength, but filled with the ſpirit; and as I lay on the ſaid Lords day, this Scripture came in with a very great ſtrength in the middeſt of Divine contemplation; it was ſpoken this ſecond time, after two daies I will revive thee, then I was drawn forth to ask of God his mind to his hand-maid from that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118503:19"/>Scripture, and my requeſt was thus anſwered; one day with me, ſaith the Lord, is as a thouſand, and a thouſand as one day; but then I ſaid, Lord, reveal the meaning of two daies, and it was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently given in, the two da<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es are two weeks, after two weeks, I will recover thee; a perſwaſion came in with great confidence in believing, that at that ſeaſon God unlooſed the bands of my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, he would unlooſe the weakneſs of my body; though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to reaſon it was even that night two weeks, that my ſoul was ſet at liberty that my body ſhould be healed; and God ſpake thus to me, did I not tell thee I would work a wonder in Iſrael? and did I not ſay unto thee, if thou wouldſt believe, thou ſhalt ſee the glory of thy God? theſe Scripture languages were ſpoken to me in the ſpirit, encouraging me to believe, though the body ſhould grow weaker, as it did afterward, and after the ſecond appearing of God, I deſired rather to be out of the body then in it, and when I breathed forth to God how I ſhould live in the body, it was anſwered me, to the glory of thy God, is not my grace ſufficient for thee? and art thou afraid to live in the body for fear of the ſtrength of corruptions? Sin ſhall not have dominion over thee, for thou art not under the Law, but under Grace, and through the ſtrength of thy Saviour, thou ſhalt be able to conquer all thy enemies, and get the victory over the greateſt Giant-corruption and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; therefore be not faithleſs, but believing, it is for my glory thy recovery; then I ſaid, Lord, do with me what thou wilt; if thou beeſt glorified in it, whatſoever thy ſervant ſuffers, it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not; when the Lord told me of that glory he would have in my recovery, my ſpirit was ſatisfied in urging it to God any more to take me out of the body. Now I looked for a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unfolding of God in this thing, now I knew it ſhould be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſealed to me, but I knew not the time when God would ſeal it to me; ſo that when my friends deſired me to ſettle things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning outward affairs, nothing but death being expected and feared by them, and to my own ſence and feeling, and yet belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved otherwiſe; and I deſired my friends to wait a while, for I told them I believed a recovery, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> told them upon what grounds, but I bid them be ſilent, for if God had a purpoſe to take me hence, he would reveal it to me; but I told them, ſurely I ſhould be raiſed here by a mighty power, for I knew it muſt be a great power to raiſe up one ſo dead in the body, that could not riſe out
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118503:19"/>of my bed all that fortnight, but as five lifted me out one night; and I was ſo extream earthy, even as lead, that they had much ado to lift me into bed again, and I ſlept not, but talked night and day, the pourings forth of the ſpirit was ſuch, when I did ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and that was but little, but then I felt my pain and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs very much; now the greateſt extremity did not affright me, though ſometimes my bones hath been ſhaken in my fleſh, my joints unlooſed, and ſometimes great pains, as if my bones had been pulled aſunder: ſuch torture hath ſeized upon me, and ſick fits; that the parties which watched by me hath bowed me double, to keep breath in me, when I have been cold, and my breath cold within me, and to ſence a breathing out my laſt breath, ſo that my friend that watched with me, deſired to call other friends, but I intreated her to wait; much ado I had to ſpeak, yet at that inſtant God told me my breath ſhould be given me, and the vitals of my ſpirits reſtored that were ſinking, the Lord gave me faith to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and I found at that time the power of the moſt high.</p>
               <p>And the next day about the ſame hour I had an extream fit of ſhaking, to the amazement of thoſe that ſtood by, and I deſired a friend to raiſe me up in the bed, and as ſhe held me, ſhe askt me why I ſhook ſo; I told her the earthly Tabernacle muſt be ſhaken, and God would lay it lower before he reſtored it, that ſo his power may be made manifeſt, which he ſpake of at the beginning of my weakneſs; and this extremity came on me after the ſecond perſwaſion given me by my God from that Scripture ſpoken of which came to me on the firſt day of the week.</p>
               <p>On the third day of the week, the Lord ſent me Mr. <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil,</hi> Miniſter of Gods word, who aſſoon as I beheld, I could not but ſay, behold the man of God, ſuch joy was in my ſpirits, which I could not but utter forth; when I ſaw the Saints I was mightily filled with rejoycing, and after I had declared thoſe Revelations given into my ſpirit to this Miniſter of God, and other Saints that were then by, and the Spirit came with ſuch a mighty gale upon me, that though I deſired to be ſlow to ſpeak, and ſwift to hear, yet then I could not; &amp; when they deſired me to tel them of the diſtemper of my body, when I have but ſpoke a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of that, I have been tyred ſo, that I told them, to ſpeak of my body, was but loſt time; but if they would hear of Divine things;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118503:20"/>I was free from them, I moved in the right ſphear, and was in my center; it was my delight to tell of the unfoldings of God, for as I told them it was my deſire to ſpend, and to be ſpent for the Lord Jeſus; and when they deſired me to take to creatures, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them I would, but I could not; they wiſhed me to take the advice of the Phyſician, I told them I had not faith to make uſe of him, and whatever is not of faith is ſin; and beſides, I told them, I could not get down any thing my ſtomack was ſo weak and cloſed up, many arguments they brought to me, but God gave in anſwers to all of them; but after thus ſpeaking, they were about to go away, and not to praiſe and pray with me, but there was ſuch an earneſtneſs ſtirred up within me to entreat prayer; that I never deſired any with that eagerneſs and fervency of ſpirit to pray as I did Mr. <hi>Greenhil,</hi> though he told me he would, but that it would weaken my Tabernacle, and he ſaid the waters many times ariſe ſo high, that they waſh down the banks, yet I could not let him go, till he had joyned in praiſes with me, and prayer for me; and to me it appeared ſuch a prayer of faith, that I never heard him pray ſo, and when the Spirit breathed in him for my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, he ſaid Lord ſtrengthen thine hand-maids perſwaſion; no ſooner were theſe words gone forth, which I am ſure was from the Spirit, and it was the purpoſe of God at that time to ſeal to that which was before ſpoken; therefore God ſo ſtirred me up, ſo to deſire prayer, becauſe that was the time of Gods intentions to give me a farther teſtimony; and as the words before mentioned came forth, it was ſtampt upon my ſpirits in much glory and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in theſe words; it is finiſhed, be it according unto thy faith; then I was confident without ſtaggering, that I ſhould recover, though I ſaw no probability in body, for that continued ſtill weaker and like earth, even the Sent of a dead carcaſe: but God carried me up abundantly in believing, that after this I ſaid: Friends, now I dare not queſtion any more, becauſe it is the voice of my God, that hath ſpoken it, and no deluſion; therefore I ſaid I am not afraid to tell the whole world, if I could ſee them, that God would raiſe me up at the time, that though the ſtript me of my ſtrength of body, he would reſtore it to me again, even at that night as I ſaid before, God making it out to me by Scripture, and after ſealing it to me.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:118503:20"/>
               <p>But to tell you how I was that night after Mr. <hi>Greenhil</hi> was gone; about the ninth hour, that night an extream pain ſeized on me, and my throat was very ſore and a ſwelling in my mouth, which even ſtopt my breath, and Satan violently ſeized on me, tempting me ſtrongly, that my breath that night might be ſtopt, and I might have a quincy in my throat, and death take me away ſuddenly, and then what will become of thy faith? No ſooner came this attempt, though very ſtrongly, yet ſtronger was he that was within me, then he that is of the world, and God gave me a word to ſay to Satan immediatly, which was this; avoid Satan, God is true, and thou art a lyer, it is the voice of my God, I have heard, and I know it is true, and ere morning my throat and mouth was healed; then I ſaw the love and power of God in that, but the Fever continued very much burning, &amp; my body outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly like a clod of earth cold, and yet in great ſweats, that I have been as in a reaking bath, when I have done ſpeaking, that I have been removed from one ſide of the bed to the other, yet nothing troubled me, neither cold nor heat, and it was a time of extream heat to others, they could not tell how to endure it, it was ſo faint a time, yet I complained of nothing, the carryings up of God were ſuch, that when company was reſtrained from me through the tender love of my friends, yet I could not but utter my voice, ſuch a mighty ſpirit of prayer was poured on me, in my weakneſs, that when none were with me, I could not keep ſilence what the Spirit ſpake in me, as <hi>David</hi> ſaies, ſo may I, that when I thought to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent I could not, my ſpirits rejoyced exceedingly to be ſpeaking of what I ſaw and heard; and as I often ſaid, O Saints, that you did but feel, ſee and taſt with me, what unutterable joy would you have! I could wiſh you all as I am except my weakneſs, and if I could ſpeak to you as it was ſpoken to me (I told them) it would appear far more glorious: but it come from men at ſecond hand, which is as water running through the channel but it came to me as water out of a fountain, that is, from one it came not ſo ſwiftly into me; now it came ſo faſt from me, to the aſtoniſhment of friends, that one ſo weak, not able to ſit up in my bed, a quarter of an hour, but in great pain, though they put pillows to keep me up, and this was after God had ſealed to his own word that I ſhould recover, for then I could have waited if it had been never
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118503:21"/>ſo long, and in never ſuch great torture, as I told the Saints now, I could lye upon a Rock till the time of deliverance come; had God ſet a longer time I could have been content, it was ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to me to wait after the Sealing, For ſtill when the tempter would tell me, when I laid my eyes together, I ſhould be ſtruck dead, and when I ſaid I ſhould recover, the Devil told me I ſhould not, but death ſhould deprive me of my confidence; yet no at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts ſtartled me, or weakned my faith in the leaſt meaſure, for God was ſtill at hand to deliver; Many times Sathan ſtrove to ſhatter my confidence, but as my Saviour prayed for me when he was here upon the earth in praying for all that ſhould believe, ſo he was ready to reſcue me upon all occaſions, both night and day, praiſed be his holy name, which told me he would not fail my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations, but according as he had given me faith to believe, it ſhould be to me; and ſtill my Saviour encouraged me to believe, and I ſhould ſee his glory.</p>
               <p>And the day after Mr. <hi>Greenhill</hi> was gone, Mr. <hi>Simpſon</hi> came, he was with me the fourth day after I kept my bed, and I told him how greatly God had appeared to me, for which I deſire to praiſe the great God; and after this Trumpeter in <hi>Iſrael</hi> (for I could not but give him that title ſo ſoon as I ſaw him come into the Chamber) and aſſoon as he had praiſed and was gone, I was troubled that he did not more queſtion me, and bring arguments againſt me, for trial, I know true gold is made more manifeſt by the touchſtone, and it is more purified in the Furnace, and appears from droſs.</p>
               <p>But to tell you of the ſecond coming of this Embaſſador of Chriſt, now I beheld the Spirit of God moving in him to ſpeak in a ſoul-ſearching manner, though he told me I might be deluded, and alſo telling me that many had been deluded, and he therefore Exhorted me to have a care that I believed upon good grounds, and told me I might make uſe of the means, and partake of the creatures, and to look up to God to give me ſleep, many Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Examinations he uſed to me, which I much rejoyced in, for my faith was the more confirmed; and while I was upon the Tryal, God came in with a mighty ſtrength, telling me that I was not deluded, but he would raiſe me without means by his mighty power, as he did <hi>Lazarus</hi> out of the grave; at my firſt ſickening I did uſe the means, I took things, but they did me no good, I was
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118503:21"/>the more tortured, and felt my ſelf the worſe, becauſe God came not in the means, it took no Effect, God had a further work to ſhew to his people. <hi>And the Lord bid me tell theſe things in Gath, and publiſh them in Aſhkelon;</hi> fear not ſaith God to tell it to the greateſt Monarch of the world if thou beeſt called to it, <hi>For I thy God am with thee;</hi> And I, ſaith the Lord, will ſtrengthen thee in all difficulties that thou ſhalt meet withall.</p>
               <p>But now I ſhall tell you Saints, how God preſented himſelf to me in many ſimilitudes, which I never heard mentioned before by any, they were brought immediately from God and Scripture, preſented that I never took notice of before, and God ſweetly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted them to my ſpirit; God firſt filled me with contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about the Trinity, which was ſweeter then the hony and the honycomb to my ſpiritual pallat; it came in ſuch a Majeſty to me, that I am not able to ſet it forth, it ſwallowed up my ſpirits; But in deſiring to declare it to the Saints, this ſimilitude of a Tree was ſet before me; God the root, his Son Chriſt the Tree, the Spirit the Sap, and as the Root, and Tree, and Sap are but one in a natural ſence, for the Sap and Tree looked on in the Root, there is but one ſubſtance which lies hid till ſuch time as it puts forth it ſelf in a Tree, and then the Tree appears; but it is covered with a Bark or Rinde, and the Sap is diſcovered running from the Root, through the Tree into the Branches, which Sap is not ſo diſcovered as when the bark is peeled off the Tree: yet then it cannot be diſcerned in the nature of it; So the Father Son and Spirit are one in that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious eſſential incomprehenſible Being, making themſelves forth in thee, 3 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7. God lies hid in the Root, man is not capable to know what he is, no more then man is capable to know what ſweetneſs is in the Root of a Tree while it lies hid, till it appear in the Tree and Sap; ſo when this one God appears in the Tree, the Lord Jeſus, then his ſweetneſs begins to break forth, and is made forth more by the Sap, the Spirit; But I deſired the Lord to ſhew me this ſimilitude by Scripture, in which he opened the Trinity by way of Root, Tree, and Sap; God is ſaid to be love, and he that dwelleth in God dwelleth in love; So that from this, God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared as the Root of mans happineſs, being infolded in the firſt perſon in Trinity from Eternity; by this Root, which the Scripture calls love, the firſt glorious perſon in Trinity appearing in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond perſon the Tree; But how is he called a Tree in Scripture?
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118503:22"/>It was preſently preſented before me, that he was that Tree ſpoken of in Paradiſe, that Tree of life, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. But how may the ſpirit be called ſap from Scripture? Thus it is called a holy anoynting, it is compared to Oyle, <hi>To the Oyntment</hi> Pſal. 133.2. <hi>which was upon Arons head, and ran down upon his beard, and ſo to the skirts of his garment;</hi> And from the word Oyl or Oyntment, ſo the third glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious perſon in Trinity is likened unto ſap, and thus it appeared to me that as the ſap runs from the Root through the Tree into the branches, ſo the Spirit, the holy Oyle runs from out of the Root, which is the Father through the Tree, which is the Son, into the Branches; For ſo the Saints are called in Scripture Branches of the Vine Chriſt Jeſus, and as the Sap drops into the branches and twigs of a Tree, which cauſes them to live and appear green, and the efficacy of this Sap produces fruit, it is very Vertual, it deſcends of its vertue into the leavs, which elſe would wither; as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the fall of the leaf, when the Sap returns into the Root, the leaves wither and fail; And as there is a Vertual Union of the Root, Tree, and Sap, and Branches, and Fruit, and Leaves; ſo there is a glorious Union and Congruity, that the Saints have in the holy Trinity, their life is in the Root, and it appears in the Tree, and manifeſted by the Sap to the Branches, the Elect appear dead till the Spirit which is the ſap quickneth them, and no fruit is brought forth, though they may have a profeſſion, yet it is but as dead leaves which falls and crumbles to duſt; So that from the ſpirit ſlows ſweet waters, it produces ſound fruit, it makes alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors green and lively; and as when the bark is pilled of the Tree, the Sap is more diſcerned: ſo when the humanity of Chriſt is taken from the Saints view, then the ſpirit was more diſcerned. Therefore ſays Chriſt, it is expedient that I go away, that ſo you may have a fuller ſight of the Spirit. He that believes (as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath ſaid,) <hi>Out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living waters,</hi> this ſpake he of the ſpirit which thoſe ſhould receive that believed, that was not yet given, becauſe Chriſt was not yet glorified; this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture appeared, very glorious to me, and I ſet the efficacy of it on my ſpirits, and God told me that the time was not yet far off ere he would pour out his Spirit upon his Children, and take away that skin of formality that hath lain ſo long upon their ſights, and that drowſineſs or ſleepineſs of ſpirit that hath ſeized upon them, and baptize them with the holy Spirit, which ſhould break forth as fire
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118503:22"/>among them, ſo that they ſhall be filled with the Song of the Lamb, and they ſhall behold their King of <hi>Salem,</hi> which is King of peace riding on his white horſe of Triumph, Conquering and to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer; The Saints ſhall overcome by the Lamb, by the word of his teſtimony; Thus mightily God came into my ſpirits, which was exceeding ſweet to me, which cauſed me to Exhort the Saints to ſtudy the Trinity more, of which one thought is more worth then ten thouſand words.</p>
               <p>And further I ſhall tell you Saints, in other Scriptures how God did preſent himſef, as concerning <hi>Jacobs</hi> ladder, as it is written, <hi>In his ſleep he ſaw a Viſion, a Ladder ſet upon the earth, the top of it reached to heaven, and he beheld the Angels of God Aſcending, and Deſcending on it, and behold the Lord ſtood above it;</hi> and this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie was held forth in it, the Ladder ſignifies Chriſt a Saviour, the top reaching to heaven, and from thoſe words the Lord ſtood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove it, and it reached to the earth, in that the humane nature of Chriſt was preſented, the Divine nature aſſumeing to it ſelf fleſh, and whereas it is ſaid, the Angels of God Aſcended and Deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on it, in that was held forth the ſweet recourſe the Saints have in Jeſus Chriſt, in his Death, in his Reſurrection and Aſcention to glory. This appeared very ſweet to me, but I cannot ſet forth things ſo fully as they came in, and God in the night ſet before me <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> Riddle of the Lyon and the hony, out of the eater came forth meat, and out of the ſtrong came ſweetneſs; By Lyon is meant Chriſt, who is called in Scripture, <hi>the Lyon of the Tribe of Juda,</hi> and by Honey is meant that ſweetneſs that lies wrapt up in Jeſus Chriſt, conſidered as a Lyon yet full of ſweetneſs; And as it is ſaid, <hi>out of the eater come forth meat,</hi> Chriſt is that eater which eats up the ſpirits, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>the Zeal of thine houſe hath eaten me up,</hi> and the word might ſet out that vertue which comes from the Lord Jeſus, <hi>which is the bread of life,</hi> in which we have life for ever, and out of the ſtrong came ſweetneſs, that is, <hi>out of the Lyon of the Tribe of Juda</hi> flows all our ſweetneſs and raptures of joy, and as <hi>Sampſon</hi> told them, <hi>Except they had plowed with his Heyfer, they could not have found out his Riddle;</hi> So the great God ſpake to me in the whiſperings of his Spirit; and ſaid; in believing in my ſon Chriſt, which is typed out by an Heyfer, and Plowing may ſignifie believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that in believing in thy Saviour thou ſhalt underſtand my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets; God I may ſay ſpoke to me as a man ſpeaks to his friend,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118503:23"/>but in a far more tranſcendent manner; and <hi>Ionathan</hi> ſpoken of in the 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. it came thus to me, that though he was ſo faint, that he climbed on his hands and feet, and his eyes were dim with faintneſs, and no ſooner had he taken of the hony that dropt out of the rock, but his eyes were enlightned; ſo as ſoon as there is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilling from that rock Chriſt upon the ſpirits, then it taſtes ſuch ſweetneſs which ſtrengthens the fainting ſpirits, and this was that which made me ſay; oh come Saints, taſte and ſee! did you but know what I feel you would admire with me: oh how ſtrong am I in the Lord, and in the power of his might!</p>
               <p>When I have cloſed my eyes, thinking to ſleep, they have on a ſudden been forced open, and upon the Sun ſhining in the room, this was declared to me; ſeeſt thou how the Sun ſhines in beams and ſtreams accompanied with ſhadows? and I ſaid, Lord, why doth it not ſhine as in the body of it, why doth it not ſhine ſo on the Earth, as in the Firmament? It was anſwered me, ſhould it ſhine on the Earth, as it is in the Firmament, it would ſuddenly burn up all things on the earth, no fruits of the earth, nor any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture could live or breathe, and therefore that it might be for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the fruits of the earth, and of all creatures, it was ſpread forth in the beams and ſtreams of it; ſo the Lord ſaid to me, ſhould I thy God dwell in thee, as I am in my eſſentiall glory, thou couldſt not breathe in the body, but immediatly thou wouldſt dye in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, it could not bear ſuch a weight of glory: therefore I ſhine on thee on beams and ſtreams of glory, which produces thoſe effects ſpoken of in Scripture; I was filled with joy: now I knew not wherefore God ſpake this to me, till a while after: I was going to ſpeak of it, and this voice came to me, This was brought to thee for the rectifying of thy Judgement: the erring ſpirit ſhall come to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29. laſt: now I conſidered how I had erred, in that I had held forth before I ſickned, that God dwelt eſſentially in his Saints, when I conſidered in Scripture, where it is ſaid, God in us, and likewiſe when I viewed <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. which holds out the fruits and operations of the ſpirit, I was at a loſs in my ſpirits concerning this, nor could not make it out, nor be convinced by any, till God ſatisfied me; and ſo in many other things none could give me light, till the light of lights came, and then my ſpirit was full of praiſes.</p>
               <p>Another time when I laid my ſelf to ſleep, ſomething as it were
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118503:23"/>pulled me by the ſhoulder, with this voice, it is better for thee to wake, I will ſhew thee thy Saviour in the Mount; then was ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me Jeſus taking up <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> into the Mount, and his transfiguration before them, which to me ſhined forth very glorious, that I ſaid as the diſciples ſaid, Lord it is good to be here; and that of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> appearing, in that was preſented to me the glory of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and from <hi>Elias</hi> was diſcovered the glory of the Prophets, and both theſe glories meeting in the glory of Jeſus Chriſt; Oh how this did enamour the ſpirits of the Diſciples, and herein they manifeſted the ſtrength of their delight in ſaying, <hi>And let us build here three Tabernacles, one for thee, one for</hi> Moſes, <hi>and one for</hi> Elias, it was with them as it is with a man that delights and affects a place, he deſires to take up his abode there, ſo the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples would fain have been continually beholding that glory, but while he yet ſpake, a bright cloud overſhadowed them, and behold a voice out of the cloud, ſaying, <hi>This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed, hear you him;</hi> The ſoul wrapt up in the glorious diſcovery of the brightneſs of God, would fain be always in that condition, but that God ſeeth it good to draw a cloud to overſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow them; a cloud, but not a thick black one, but a bright one: which noted thus much, That let the greateſt diſcovery of glory which cauſed the face to ſhine be withdrawn, (God doth not leave his without glory, though in a cloud) yet there appears brightneſs and a ſweet voice, telling the Saints that they ſhall hear and ſee that inviſible glory ſounded forth in the Son, by that word <hi>hear ye him;</hi> now we ſee him as in a glaſs, but we ſhall ſee him as he is, when we ſhall be lifted up for ever above all clouds.</p>
               <p>At another ſeaſon when I have ſhut my eyes, immediatly they have been uncloſed, and my Saviour preſenting his ſpeech to me that he ſaid to his Diſciples, when he was to depart from them, and that was this; <hi>Verily verily, I ſay unto you, I will drink no more of the fruit of this Vine, till I drink it new in my Fathers Kingdom;</hi> This came in, in ſuch a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, that I was not able to underſtand it, but it was diſcovered a little, thus, That the ſpirit was held out in an embleme of wine when as Chriſt was upon the earth, but it ſhall after his Aſcention break forth in a new, and far more glorious manner, like new wine, more ſweet and perſpicuous, ſo that it was made forth to me to be meant the pourings forth of the Spirit. Now I ſhall tell you Saints, of more
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118503:24"/>illuſtrations and interpretations given in from the ſight of hearbs and flowers, as that of the ſweet Bryar, why ſweet and yet thorny, we ſee the moſt ſweeteſt enjoyment that this world can preſent to the creature, hath a thorn accompanying it, and likewiſe Chriſt is a very ſweet fragrant ſmell to his friends, but to his enemies a thorn; and concerning flowers this was given in, the variety of ſmells pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from them, and the variety of colours, in which was held forth the variety of beauties, and ſweetneſs flowing from my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; one thing I minded in the marigold, it being brought before my eyes, I ſaw pleaſures and honours, and the greateſt preferments here guilded outſides, but black in the middle; ſo I ſaw the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus glory to the Saints: but black to the wicked, even as the mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gold appears like gold, in the middle black; and ſo likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſpice. A few nutmegs being preſented from a friend to me thus much was hinted forth, mercy and love coming from the friend of friends, not ſingle but double mercies, and this was preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo from the hardneſs of it being ſtony, ſo Chriſt is the corner ſtone, and as the nutmeg is barky without, and gives but little ſmell till it be grated, and then the ſmell is very fragrant, and the oylneſs of it appears: ſo Chriſt when he is grated upon the ſpirits, that is, when he is made known unto the ſoul by the ſpirit. Oh what ſweet fragrant ſmell comes into every faculty of the ſoul! And the ſpirit that holy oyl or unction drops down upon the whole man, even as there is a diſcovery of the oyl in the nutmeg, when it is grated. Truly Saints, did you but feel in the reading of this that ſweet odour that I found in my ſpirits, you could not but praiſe with me. And when I ſaw the fruits of the earth, many inſtructions were given in, as in the ſight of Cherries I ſaw the blood of my Saviour, and ſuch fruits which was firm in the outſide, &amp; yet hollow, and a ſtone in the middle of them, ſo all things here below are hollow, though they appear firm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. Laſt, <hi>the erring ſpirit ſhall come to underſtand, and the murmuring ſpirit ſhall learn doctrine.</hi> The Lord made this Scripture very ſweet to me, and I was incouraged to comfort drooping Saints, to caſt their ſouls upon Jeſus Chriſt, who calls to the weary and heavy laden to come to him, that is to believe in him whom the father hath ſent. And I alſo was filled with ſuch a ſpirit of boldneſs, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>the righteous are as bold as a Lion,</hi> ſo that whereas I am of a fearful ſpirit by nature, yet God then carryed me forth to ſpeak
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118503:24"/>abundantly to all that came to me, whether they were of high or low degree. And ſuch relentings of ſpirit was in me towards backſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that I deſired to weep tears of blood, if it had been poſſible to have gained them. Oh friends, how did I thirſt after the wel<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are of every one! that they that told me, they lived in the ſpirit, I told <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem how ſweet a thing walking in the ſpirit w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, which will teach to intreat when we are reviled, and to be of a lamblike ſpirit when enemies reproach, that ſo we might imitate that lamb which took away ſin; and ſure had not the ſpirit of God gone along with exhortations, they would not have took ſo much effect upon many ſpirits. I think hardly any came but they went away affected, both young and old; ſuch was the love of God thus to break forth, which had I the tongue of Angels, I could not expreſs. I deſire it may ſhine forth in all my actions, for truly the work of God is marvellous in my eyes; and that Scripture of Chriſt telling his Diſciples, that they ſhould ſet upon twelve thrones, Judging the twelve Tribes of Iſrael, by that word twelve thrones, was much ſet forth to me, the great dignity of the Saints. The Lord acquaint us more with the Spirit in the letter, then ſhall we be able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand every truth, <hi>and the erring ſpirit ſhall come to underſtand, and the murmuring ſpirit ſhall learn doctrine;</hi> as God much perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me that that ſpirit of formality, which hath lain ſo long upon the Saints, ſhould be taken off, and the Lord gave me faith to believe for the Saints, and me thinks I ſee them groaning after the pourings forth of the ſpirit, and ſurely the time ſhall not be long ere the Lord will ſatisfie the groaning ſoul, and anſwer the expectations of the Saints, for as in God are hid treaſures of wiſdom and knowledge, ſo every treaſure ſhall be opened to the Saints in the appointed time, therefore the Saints ſhall wait for it.</p>
               <p>Many times God appeared in viſions of glory to me, as I lay wrapt up in the ſpirit, I beheld a glorious ſtar ſhining exceeding bright, and the bright morning ſtar the Lord Jeſus was much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented into my thoughts, and concerning <hi>Fzekiels</hi> viſion, he ſaw by the River <hi>Chebar,</hi> it is ſaid he ſaw viſions of God, which word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought immediatly from God to me, it was very ſweet; this was given into me, that when Saints are in affliction, in reſpect of their outward man, though they be in great ſtraits; yet nothing can deprive them of the breakings forth of their God, nay, then when
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118503:25"/>the creature is at a low ebb in the outward man, the Lord is pleaſed to viſit the creature with a full Sea of glory, and ſaith to the Saints, be you open ye everlaſting gates, that the King of glory may enter in. Oh how ſweet this Scripture was ſpoken in the ſpirit to me! I can but hint things forth, and ſpeak partly of what I found; Saints, I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion not but in your own experiences, what hath been declared, will be more cleared to you by the ſpirit, though I am able to declare them but ſtammeringly, yet theſe things came pla<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nly into my ſpirits, and with a mighty fulneſs, that I could evidently ſay, theſe are the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of an infinite God, and no deluſion, praiſed be the moſt high; my mouth was full of praiſes, and begged of all that came nigh me to praiſe, that had the ſpirit of praiſes; and ſtill I was entreating the Saints to ſpeak ſweetly and gently to all perſons, that they might appear to be the ſheep of the great ſhepheard Chriſt; I told them how it b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>came Saints to be of a meek ſpirit, and I was not aſhamed to confeſs that I was by nature of a contentious perverſe ſpirit, which I now loathed; and every proud thought was an abomination to me, and I told the Saints they were to look up for ſtrength, to walk as people of another Nation, that it might be ſaid, they are the people of the living God, who have the mark of God in all their actions. Now friends, I ſhall tell you once concerning my raiſing from weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſtrength, from pain to eaſe, and that both to the amazement of my ſelf, and thoſe that were preſent with me; but oh that I might never forget to praiſe the Lord, not only in word, but in my holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation! in all theſe diſcoveries that have been related, my body ſtill grew weaker and weaker, and the Sent of dead ſouls turned out of the grave was ſtill in my noſtrils, and my body like unto a clod of earth, and pain working up to my heart; the day before my recovery, one Captain <hi>Harris</hi> prayed by me, and in that prayer I was mightily ſtrengthened in believing, and could not but ſay, Lord, why may not I be raiſed now? And anſwer was ſuddenly darte<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into my ſpirit, I the Lord can raiſe thee now, but thou ſhalt be raiſed at that time that thy God hath given thee to believe; Oh how ſweet was this anſwer in my Spirits, that though I had a deſire then to ariſe, and I ſtrove to liſt up my ſelf, yet I could not, for the Lord told me his time was not yet, and untill the day of deliverance came, I was not onely weak and ſick in body, but my ſpirits were very dead, not activity or livelineſs in them all the forenoon, but in the afternoon this Scripture was handed by my father to me; why is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118503:25"/>thy ſoul troubled? why is thy ſpirit ſad within thee? <hi>Believe in God, believe alſo in me,</hi> John. 14.1. in this I was mightily refreſht, and my ſpirits quickned, and faith much ſtrengthened; not that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief did ſeize upon me at any time, after God had ſealed theſe things upon my ſpirit, though Satan told me that at that inſtant I believed I ſhould recover, my breath ſhould be taken out of my body; now it did not fear me, God ſtill perſwading me that his power ſhould be made manifeſt, but I ſtill grew to the earth, my body waxt very cold, and in clamy ſweats, that thoſe that had been preſent with perſons when their breath departed from them, they could not imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, or liken me to any other but a dying perſon; to my own feeling and ſence my hands were dead, and the reſt of my body very liveleſs, my breath to my own ſence was even departing from me, this was about ſix or ſeven a clock that night: then I was raiſed, and ſuddenly God poured a mighty ſpirit of prayer upon me, that I felt my breath which was taking leave of my body, heated, and I pleaded with God in believing, for the accompliſhment of his promiſe, and <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was ſet before me, his faith ſtrong, though he ſaw no ſacrifice, he believed God would raiſe an <hi>Iſaac</hi> out of the aſhes; ſo God carried my ſpirits up contrary unto ſence, and when the ſpirit of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was off me, then god inſtructed me what to ſay to the Saints that ſtood by quivering and fearing, not being able to ſee this accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed by the eye of faith, it being very contrary unto ſence, and when the ſpirit making uſe of me had done incouraging the Saints, telling them they ſhould ſurely ſee the work of the Lord; and after thus ſpeaking, I fell in a trance, in which I ſaw the glory of my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour exceedingly, but I cannot ſpeak what I ſaw; and this laſted about a quarter of an hour, and when it began to wear away, this voice was given into my Spirits, I ſay ariſe, walk and praiſe me; ſet forth my glory; this came with a mighty ſtrength, that I felt ſtrength given into my limbs that were deadeſt, firſt revived, and a ſong of <hi>Hallelujah</hi> ſounded into my ſpirits, ſaying, now ſing praiſe unto the great God, and to the Lamb that ſits upon the throne, and great joy came into my ſpirits from the holy Spirit; and no ſooner did God ſay ariſe, walk, but I was lifted up by the power of the moſt high God from my bed, and I called for my clothes, all pain was ceaſed, the Fever left me, and I put on my clothes, and as ſoon as I came out of my bed, death pangs ſeized extraordinarily upon me,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118503:26"/>my heart ſtrings were ready to crack, and I was even ſinking, a ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in my head being very great alſo, and my ſpirit ſuddenly was drawn forth to ſay, Lord, wilt thou now nullifie the work? and ſhall thy hand maid now be deſerted? and the Lord anſwered me, am not I thy ſtrength? and I found ſtrength immediatly, and could walk about the room without fainting, or any body to help me, and my ſtomack was opened that I could let down broth, which before I could not; and I continued up till midnight, praiſing God with the Saints; and after I was laid in my bed, I could not ſhut my eyes to ſleep all that night, to think that on ſuch a ſudden ſo great an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be made, that I could lye down free from all pain and diſtemper that I felt before, and ſo I grew ſtill, every day more ſtrength was given in to me; on the fourth day at night, thus God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and on the firſt day of the week after, which is called the Sabbath day, I went abroad to the praiſe and glory of my father, which hath ever ſince continued my health, and I minded thus much in Gods raiſing of me, he doubled his power in recovering me once and again, when I began to faint, and alſo the week following God told me I ſhould have my perfect ſtrength, which week was the third day, inſtanced in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>And thus Saints, having an incouragement from the Spirit of Truth, to ſet before your view ſome of the experiences God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into me, through his own free love, but a creature-capacity cannot contain all the incomings of God I had while I lay in my ſickneſs; but being very much importuned by ſome friends, I have fulfilled their deſires, through the aſſiſtance of God, in ſetting forth as much as was brought to my remembrance, I being a weak worthleſs crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a babe in Chriſt, which makes his power the more manifeſt.</p>
               <p>And now Saints, I intreat your prayers continually for me.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:118503:26"/>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is further added a ſhort diſcourſe, written eight years ago, weighty and precious, for that it pierceth through the veil, ſearcheth into the inſide of things, and giveth ſome hint of things now looked for by many, but then more hid and covered; whereby the wiſdom and depth of that ſpirit that is in her may ſufficiently appear: we find this inſcription before it, as the title of it, <hi>viz.</hi> The third moneth, the year, 1646. A declaration of Revelations, or the unfoldings of God to the ſoul in viſions of glory; the mind of God made known by his ſpirit, not onely concerning its own particular, but others alſo, according to promiſe; thy God will ſhew thee great things to come, <hi>Ier.</hi> 33.3.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>After an extraordinary appearance of God, he yet ſhewed me more, and hath been, and is ſtill very mighty in all his operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, working ſuch a frame of ſpirit, ſubjecting it ſelf unto its God, in all the ſeveral kinds of providences, &amp; ſundry diſpenſations that it meets with, ſeeing a ſweet harmony in contraries, in things that pleaſe not fleſh and blood in every thing enjoyed, and in nothing enjoyed, God appears all in all, ſo that when pipes are cut off, and ſtreams ceaſe running, and not onely ſtreams without, but alſo within, ſeem to be dryed up; even then when the heart and ſtrength fails, nay, though there be not any feeling of the movings, and actings, and flowings of the Spirit, though the beams are claſpt in the body of the Sun, it is not the beams that are my center, but the Son it ſelf; unto this height will the ſpirit bring the Saints, until which time, there is a living upon ſomething below God; I by the ſpirit am able to tell Saints, that God is about to take them off reſting on any thing below himſelf, and ſurely God will
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118503:27"/>lead them through the wilderneſs, but they ſhall march on trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly, becauſe the captain of their ſalvation ſhal go before them, ſo that Scorpions, and fiery Serpents ſhall not devour them; God will put a hook in the noſtrils of the Leviathan, the flood of the dragon ſhall not ſwallow up the woman, which is the Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. becauſe the child Jeſus, which is the man child ſpoken of, is within the Saints; the heavens of God moſt expect to be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by God, but not from God, but from all things below God: me thinks I ſee by the light of the ſpirit the time of deſolation, and reſtauration drawing nigh: Oh Saints, ſtand upon your watch, for certainly Antichriſt, which is the beaſt ſpoken of, that ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear like a Lamb but with his two horns ſhall gore as a beaſt, for ſo his nature is, though in pretences there may be the form of a Lamb, and in outward ſhew, therefore iniquity is called a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <hi>Rev</hi> 13. becauſe it worketh in a Sophiſtical manner, elſe it would not ſwallow up ſo many into its gulf; this beaſt which comes wrapt up in the skin of the Lamb, it is onely a Lamb in ſhew, not in ſubſtance, it is ſaid to come out of the earth, which ſignifies his power onely to be in the earth, and his two horns, the one is ſubtle policy, or a ſecret ſophiſtry, and the other horn an open power, the one playing the part of an underminer, the other of an open diſcoverer; the one horn worketh under ground, making the ground hollow, the other horn is a more viſible pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, puſhing thoſe that work not with them, and that would ſwallow them up into its own power, but this beaſt underſtands not the things made known by the ſpirit, to an <hi>Eliſha</hi> that the King of <hi>Syria</hi> ſpoke in his bed chamber, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 6.12. ſo that though this undermining beaſt may think to affright, in utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his voice like a dragon, yet he ſhall not ſcare the Saints from their ſtedfaſtneſs, they will follow their Lamb, where ever he goes, which Lamb will appear a Lion, to reſcue the Sheep-out of the mouth of the woolf; though they prevail ſo far as to catch the ſheep into their mouths, they ſhall not let their teeth in them, ſo as to bite them in pieces; For the Saints, their bars are iron, and their gates braſs, ſo that the ſtrongeſt Dragons teeth cannot rend Saints a ſunder; the beaſt ſhall ſo far prevail as to ſcatter them from enjoying ſome outward priviledges, nay, I believe, for a time all outward priviledges ſhall as it were be in the hand of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, he exalting himſelf <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> above all that is called God
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118503:27"/>or above him that is the true God, and ſeeking dominion in the ſeat of God, which is the Saints, into which ſeat he ſhall never come, for its Gods alone prerogative to keep his Court in the Saints, they are his throne; the Prince of the Air ſhall abide in Airy climates; Surely the footſtool of God ſhall not mount up into the throne, though the horn of policy working under ground, may, cauſe a duſt to flye about the throne, and may raiſe up ill va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours out of the bottomleſs pit, which may be offenſive, and there may and is, and will be yet a great ſmother in the Nations, ſo that the Temple ſhall hardly be diſcerned; but the King knoweth his Temple, and his place where he keeps Court, and his Subjects know him to be their Prince of peace in the midſt of wars, and ruins of the outward Court, and no ſmother ſhall make their eyes to water or wax dim, becauſe Chriſt is their ſight, and the light and being of their eye; no marvell that the Saints are ſo ſtrong ſight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, what can deprive them of their ſight? it is not the rail of the Dragon, nor the horn of the beaſt, nor the ſmoak of Antichriſt, that is able in the leaſt meaſure to dim the ſight and light of Saints: They are his houſe of glory, upon whom he ſets a defence; what Cannon can batter down that houſe that God is in? They do but beat the Air, that mannage ſubtilty to ſhakle Saints, they do but bring themſelves further into ſhakels; but what ſhall I ſay? or ſhall God ſay it? That he hath ſent the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> into the Land to bring about his own deſign, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.12. and when the great <hi>Iehovah</hi> hath accompliſhed his own purpoſe, on mount <hi>Sion,</hi> by that time ſhall the meaſure of iniquity be full, and the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of wrath ready to empty on that harlot that hath deceived the Nations; then ſhall the ſpirit appear in its full flame, burning up all droſs and rubbiſh before it; and on whom it diſplaies, its glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous rayes of beauty, there ſhall be ſuch a ſparkling, that others ſeeing the ſparks flye out ſo faſt, ſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll conclude there is fire within, and ſhall ſay, this is the very Mount of God, the City of the Holy One, and ſhall admire that fire ſhould be in the buſh, and the buſh not burnt; is it not matter of wonder, that the infinite being ſhould be in a finite being, and yet not the finite conſumed? Me thinks I ſee not only fooliſh Virgins ſlumbering and ſleeping but the wiſe Virginis are alſo in a ſlumber, but when the bridegrooms appearance ſhall be manifeſted, ſhall they ſtill lye in ſlumber? I believe otherwaies, that there ſhall be ſuch an awaking of all
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118503:28"/>things, the very foundations of all things ſhall be ſhaken by that foundation that ſhall ſtand for ever; God will ſet his Mountain on the top of all Mountains; there indeed ſhall be the munition of rocks on rocks, and one glory within another: Oh what varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are in the feaſts that the Saints bridegroom provides for them! If they be ſlumbering when his feaſts are ready, he ſounds out the golden trumpet of his ſpirit, and cauſeth a great alarm to come forth from himſelf, which immediatly awaketh the Spouſe, that it ſaith, it is the voice of my beloved, that ſaith, ariſe and come away, leave thoſe Babyloniſh garments behind, that thou haſt as it were been wrapt in; ſurely the filthy polluted rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged garments that hang upon the Lords <hi>Ioſhuaes, Zach.</hi> 3.3, 4. thoſe who are his anointed Prieſts, ſhall be ſhaken off, the white robe of Righteouſneſs ſhall be their clothing; although the evil one may hang his rags on Gods Prieſts, they ſhall not abide, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are of a royall deſcent, they are the Kings children, rags are the clothing of ſuch that ſit on dunghils, and filthy gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for ſuch that tumble in the mire; but Saints clothing is whiter then the ſnow in Salmon, purer then the pureſt thing that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall eye can behold; and this ſpirituall part of a Saint, nothing can defile, though it be of never ſuch a tainting nature; I confeſs, what ever action, or word, or thought hath any thing of fleſh in it, there is rags; for fleſh is altogether a garment of rags, the moſt refined fleſh is a filthy garment, not becoming a Saint; no gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment becomes a Saint but Jeſus Chriſt, his words and actions, and thoughts, and motions: Oh how ragged and polluted are they, if their clothing be not Jeſus Chriſt! ſtreams are full of mud that flow not from this fountain, thoſe waters are brack<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh that come not from this Conduit, no water refreſheth like that River, the ſtreams thereof are ſaid to refreſh the City of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.4. this is water of life, that in dying times makes lively, and when weeds are burnt up and wither, the plants ſhall ſprout forth and wax green, and bloſſom as the roſe, and none ſhall pluck them up.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:118503:28"/>
            <p>This ſhort word is all that we meet with of this diſcourſe, ſhe being to this day prevented of perfecting it with that enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment intended and deſired; if what hath been preſented here, may adminiſter any ſervice, either to the ſpirit of God in her, for the Juſtification thero<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which is now under a cloud, or to poor ſinners or trembling Saints, for the drawing or refreſhing of their benight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed impriſoned ſpirits, by the diſcovery of the riches &amp; glory of free love and the power of the ſpirit thus far appearing in this hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid of God it will increaſe through Chriſt our rejoycing, and abundant thankſgiving in the Lord, who is ſhortly putting a new ſong into our mouths, of Glory and triumph over all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, through the approaching and appearance of <hi>Iehovah</hi> in his glory amongſt us.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:118503:29"/>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:118503:29"/>
            <head>To the Church ſometimes meeting at AL-HOLLOWS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath pleaſed the Lord to caſt me at a diſtance from you, and your precious meetings, and ſweet, lovely, ſpirituall, deſirable enjoyments, which is more prized by me then my life or liberty, the which is now in Jeopardy; but I am through Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſtrength, not onely willing to be bound, but to dye upon ſo honourable an account, as I here ſuffer for, which is onely the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the Lords bounty, and rich grace to ſinners; my heart overflowing therewith, I cannot hold; my compaſſion and dear affections worketh forth towards Chriſts flock ſo ſtrongly, that the Anti-chriſtian Clergy hearing the ſound, were not able to bear it; and therefore, becauſe they ſaw ſo many adhere to the extraordinary things diſcovered by and through a weak inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it was grievous to them, and they would not admit of any diſcourſe with me, but cryed out to the Magiſtrate to lay bonds upon me; ſaying, we muſt not have the people ſo deluded, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me witch, deluder, Impoſter, and other vilde terms they caſt on me; and farther, ſaid I ſtirred and provoked the p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ople to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt powers, though I never ſpake as touching them ſince I came into the Country any great matter, ſo as to be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by any: but a Clergy man, one Mr. <hi>Powel,</hi> a great Teacher in theſe parts, hath taken his oath againſt me, that he heard me repeat that viſion ſpoken of in the book, which he never did;<note place="margin">Concerning the Cows and Oxen.</note> I never changed a word with him, but he coming into a friends houſe where many pretious ſouls were met, which deſired me to give an account of Gods dealings with me from a child, which I did; and I never found ſuch a broken, ſelf-abaſing, ſelf-denying frame of ſpirit in me, as then; and though this man pretended
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118503:30"/>much mildneſs towards me, yet he hath diſcovered much falſhood and rage; and becauſe I, when brought before the Rulers, ſaid I was not guilty according to the form of the bill, as it was laid together againſt me, he ſaid I denyed my Chriſt and the Spirit; But I have ſent you the bill for to paſs your judgement of my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, whether I ſhould not have denyed Chriſt if I had acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged guilty to all therein, which I muſt have done, had I ſaid guilty,<note place="margin">And they have bound me to the good Behaviour.</note> then they granted me a <hi>Travers</hi> to the next Seſſions, which is 13. weeks hence, and Captain <hi>Langdon,</hi> my faithful friend I came down with he, and Major <hi>Bauden,</hi> they were bound for my appearance, 150 l. a piece, and 1200 l. theſe dear friends, they were of the late Parliament, which the Prieſts had no good will unto, and their hatred is, becauſe their ſtanding quivers, and their fat benefices are almoſt at an end; ſure I am they are Chriſts greateſt enemies, that hath been and now is: Therefore that you may be anſwered as touching Chriſts Reign, beg that to be tumbled down, that as rotten rafters ſtand in the way; I am very ſure the Lord will cut his work ſhort in righteouſneſs and by all interruptions is making way for his Dyadem of beauty to appear, he will ſet his King up as chief Protector, let men and devils do what they can. Therefore my dear friends, be not of a doubtful mind, ſtand faſt, hold your confidence and Reſolution concerning thoſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars you firſt engaged in, at the ſetting that bleſſed meeting up, wherein the Lords preſence hath been eminently ſeen, and their ſpawn is diſcovered therby, which we thought had been free from ſting; and becauſe we own that ſecond days meeting, in joyning with your pounds a few mites, therefore we are watched by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, as if we were treacherous to the State, but here are a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of cloſe walking Saints, to what they know, and they would be more informed concerning generation-work; but warning is, to ſpeak no more in that name; and many of the ſouldiers for coming to the place where I am, are warned to their colours, and an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign under Captain <hi>Fox,</hi> which is Governour of <hi>Pendennis</hi>-caſtle, who coming to viſit my friend where I am, this Enſign <hi>Randal</hi> inviting me to his houſe, as he did the other friends, <hi>Fox</hi> hearing of it, put him out of his place; this man hath an excellent humble ſpirit, and of a very good report; I give you to underſtand theſe ſeveral puſhings of the horn, that ſo you may not onely have life
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118503:30"/>in your wreſtlings, but might have it more abundantly, ſtriving together in prayer for the day of the Lord; Man, the devil, and Anti-chriſt hath their day now; the Lord make you all ſenſible of the blaſpeming of the Lords coming and raign, truly it often makes me tremble to hear and ſee Chriſt derided and ſcoffed at by men that are great Rabbies, profeſſors indeed, but of the largeſt kind, ſuch as dare lye, and revile thoſe that are not of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: my beloved brothers and ſiſters, I am bound always to bleſs God for you, and your tender care and dear love to me doth much work up my affections for you, and draweth out my whole heart to ſerve you any way: And I knowing the workings of your deſires after my welfare, the which to underſtand will be well pleaſing to you, therefore I need not crave acceptance; The Lord whom I ſerve hath from a child kept me, and ſtill doth keep me as a Rememberer of him in his wayes, as well as rejoycing and working righteouſneſs, and he meets me in all theſe according to his promiſe; praiſe free grace for me: I intreat prayer and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes abundantly to him whoſe ſpirit and eye guided and counſelled me hither, and is ſtill my ſafety; you would admire divine love with and for me, if you knew the lettings down of all might that hath been in me, and on my behalf, the which is too large to give you an account of by writing; but in this little <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt given to you I know it will ſatisfie for the preſent. I found the benefit of your prayers this time twelve moneth, I being in Satans ſore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thraldom, which was as a Lion and a Bear to me; I ſhall never forget your labour of love for me then, and ſeeing you were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s then, which was manifeſt, even this moneth deliverance was wrought for you unworthy ſiſter; but I will bleſs God for the worthineſs of a Chriſt crucified for me, who manifeſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as a ſafety and Saviour to the utmoſt; now the Lord tryeth my faith by ſuffering the uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtime</hi> to war againſt me, and this ſtorm calls forth prayer afreſh for me, though this is but a ſmall encounter to the other, becauſe my ſtroke, I cryed out, was heavier then my groaning, and I could not find nor ſee God any where, nor in any thing as a God of love; but now mercy and goodneſs follows me day and night, and bleſſed be his name, he is an open treaſure-houſe, and much treaſure he conveyeth; pray that I may walk worthy of his Kingdom and glory. Truly my
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:118503:31"/>dear brothers &amp; ſiſters, the joy of the Lord is my ſtrength, he thinketh nothing too dear nor too much for thoſe that are ſealed to the day of Redemption; we are beholding to Chriſt, who becomes all in all; I ſee every day much leanneſs, barrenneſs and unfruitfulneſs in me, that is, in my fleſh there is ſtill ſtrugling, and fighting, and warring, but through faith in Chriſt I am an overcomer, and I am not foyled; but the more I ſee of brightneſs, the more I am filled with ſelf abhorrency, and loathing my own ways &amp; thoughts. Dear friends, I intreat an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation and advice from you, it will much add to my joy: I hope I need not uſe any motive to ſtir up and draw out your love towards me, for I having found it ready to ſerve me upon the greateſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I will not doubt of it now, though I am ſo remote; I know many waters cannot quench love, and therefore before I take leave of you for this time, I ſhall deſire that you, with my own ſoul, may be more in the practice of love, provoknig one another unto that love and unity which is a perfect bond, and fulfiller of the Law, it beareth and forbeareth, it envieth not, it takes up no evil reports againſt any of the flock, it judgeth not raſhly, it ſeeketh not her own, it ſurely praiſeth for another members enjoyment, as for its own. Seeing all members make but one body, let the ſame mind be in us, which dwelt in Chriſt Jeſus: this is the earneſt deſire of her which prayeth for you without ceaſing, and ſalutes the whole Church, and reſts</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your unworthy Siſter in the fellowſhip of the Goſpel, ANNA TRAPNEL.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> Tregaſow <hi>at Captain</hi> Langdons, <hi>near</hi> Trurow, <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 15. <hi>of the</hi> 2. <hi>moneth,</hi> 1654.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:118503:31"/>
            <head>A Letter to a Friend.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Waited for a fit opportunity and matter ſtill more fuller to preſent you with; and truly matter is ſo much, that now I cannot by writing give an account: the Lord hath been a very tender father, and hath and doth give me many expreſſions thereof; his proviſion is much, and of the beſt continually: I may ſay he is more and better to me then my deſires, for they are ſcanty, but he is fulneſs; and ever ſince I ſaw you, I have had Rivers of pleaſures, ſpiritual kindneſſes unutterable; but have I any thing to boaſt in, ſave in Free grace? No ſurely. O of Divine love will I make mention, who is the ſame yeſterday as to day, and ſo will be for ever: it alters not, and I find it ſo: but however, if I did not, yet it hath not ſo much as a ſhadow of change in it; but the Lord is a never failing por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and I every day have new experience thereof; I may well uſe that admiring ſpeech of <hi>Paul,</hi> Oh the heighht and depth, both of the wiſdom and knowledge of God, his ways are paſt finding out! yet untrodden paths hath wiſdom brought out, but to whom? even to fools, and low, baſe, vilde nothings; and this the wiſe, learned, rich, knowing ones cannot bear. True Scripture language cannot be born in theſe days, the people of this generation vote it down, and the cry is amongſt all ſorts, eſpecially the Clergy, and that of the refined ſort too, that cryes, away with Chriſts raign and Subjects, we will have our <hi>Barrabaſſes</hi> live. And ſhall not hearing and ſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt ſo deſpiſed, cauſe us to ſay with them under the Altar, that ſo many years ago cryed out, Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly? Oh, now is a time to beg God to work, now his Law of the Spirit is ſo made void, and that by thoſe that are frequent in forms, and much they plead for them, but the power is hated, as their actions witneſs, which are ſufficient Judges: but what can be ſaid to theſe things, God is for the work of the day, who ſhall then fruſtrate? Dear Sir, I ſhall now acquaint you with the tumultuous waves, and high billows that riſe up in theſe parts; I ſaid when Satan was
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:118503:32"/>letting out the noiſe of his water-ſpouts upon me, that then all the waves had gone over me, but I then ſaw his: now men hath theirs, but mens billows are eaſie to his, becauſe my father ſmileth; that which is ſweeter then the hony comb, qualifies that bitterneſs I have from unreaſonable men; <hi>Paul</hi> met with beaſts at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> I may ſay alſo I have met with beaſts in <hi>Cornwell,</hi> unreaſonable men roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon me, they endeavoured to let out to the utmoſt, their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and diſgraceful uſage, which they manifeſted, furiouſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the chamber, where I lay, at one Mr. <hi>Hills</hi> in <hi>Trurow,</hi> who invited me to his houſe to viſit his wife in his abſence, he having taken a journey to <hi>London,</hi> and is there for the preſent; and his wife deſired me to lodge there all night, the which I did, and it was told me that a warrant was out for me, and I was to be ſought for at Captain <hi>Langdons,</hi> or at Major <hi>Baudens,</hi> which is my other dear friend; but in the mean time I coming to the Town where the Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions was, they heard of it, and talk was that they would ſend for me the firſt day that I came, which was the fourth day of the laſt week, and I expected that day to have been called; but truly the Lord ſaw I was not enough prepared, for my timerous fearful nature did much work. I never having been called before a Ruler, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to conſult with fleſh and blood, but the Lord prevented them that day, that ſo I might receive ſtrength from the mount before their valleys were preſented: And bleſſed be the Lord, that night the Lord appeared lovely all night, part of it I was diſcourſing with a young Miniſter, his name is Mr. <hi>Paul,</hi> he came out of the weſt to ſee me, having heard ſuch various reports of me, for the book had given a report before I came here; and this man after ſome time ſpent in diſcourſe, I deſired him to pray, the which he did very ſweetly; he deſired it of me, but I refuſed: yet after he had done, the Lords wind filled my ſails, that I ſwom to the haven, where was pretious lading brought me, and I ſaw eminent riches and royalty, all that night continuing in prayer and ſinging till day light, ſitting in a chair, and many with me, men and women, and that Miniſter; they all came to viſit me, and the Lord was among us, and in the morning I was had to bed, being very weak, and I lay till the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon ſilent, in a very great Rapture of joy: and my enemies that acted ſecretly, and the open ones too, I beheld deviſing againſt me all the reproach and ill uſage they could, and in the afternoon, while I
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118503:32"/>was ſinging, they ſent the Conſtable for me, who made a great buſſel, ſaying, he had an order to bring me out of my bed and he pulled me, but I felt nothing, then many men and women talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, ſome ſaying he had better pleaſe God then man, he trembled, and ſaid, he muſt do what he was commanded; but in the mean time Captain <hi>Langdon</hi> went to the Bench of Juſtices, and deſired them to be pacified till the morrow, and if I were in a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity I ſhould come, he would paſs his word, and many offered body for body, but nothing would appeaſe them; they were deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to come, and ſee, and hear; ſo ſome of them came, and they made a great tumult in the houſe, and commanded my friends out of the chamber, onely ſome few ſtayed; and theſe cruel Rulers had no patience to hear, but pulled me off my pillow, and rung me by the noſe, and cauſed my eye-lids to be pulled up, but no harm I felt, nor nothing interrupted me; the which they ſeeing, ceaſed, the Lord overpowering them, though their rage was great, that they ſaid they would take me out of bed, they could not, and at that ſame time one <hi>Welſted</hi> a great Presbyterian Prieſt, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out in the chamber door, where he then ſtood, ſaying, a whip will fetch her out; but my father preſerved me from the promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Clergy, and the fiery Magiſtrate that day: And at night about ſeven of the clock, I came to ſome ordinary frame to diſcourſe, and ſaid, how quiet have I lain all this day, hath none been in the chamber? Reply was, yes, many; and then my friends came and told me all that had happened that day, for which I praiſed the Lord, and I hope I ſhall never forget that days mercy, and I bleſs the Lord I ſlept more ſweeter that night following this ſtorm, then I have done ſince I came hither, and in the morning roſe and went to the Seſſions houſe, I being ſent for, where I went with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dauntedneſs, fearful timerous nature being ſtrucken dead through mount Corrobborating: and when I came, no witneſs they had appeared for them but a Clergy one, and of him and his actings the letter to the Church makes mention, which I have made bold to ſend to you to read, or have it read among them; and further, when I ſaid, not guilty, according to that bill that was found againſt me, they had other bills againſt me, and my friend Captain <hi>Langdon</hi> too, but they could not be found, which if they could have found a bill againſt my friend, he could not have been
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118503:33"/>my ſurety: herein the Lord appeared too: and I am bound with my ſureties to Travers the indictment at the next Seſſions, there to be queſtioned by the Bench upon the ſame matter; in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment I was bound to the good Behaviour, and conſtrained to enter into Recognizance, with Sureties to appear at the next Aſſizes. And after they had thus done, they queſtioned me about the book pen'd at <hi>London,</hi> which they tendered to me, and asked me whether I would own that book as mine; I anſwered, I was not carefull to anſwer them to that matter: they then cauſed the Viſion which mentions the horns; and Cows, and Oxen, to be read, and asked me what I would ſay to that? was that mine? I ſaid as before, I would not anſwer them touching the book. I ſaying that they were not to queſtion me in this Country, concerning what was ſpoken at <hi>White-hall,</hi> for that I thought there was a Council wiſe enough to examine as to that: and they writ down, I denyed all; But as becauſe I would not accuſe my ſelf to ſatisfie their wills; Further they came to queſtion me where I had dwelt? and from what part of <hi>London</hi> I came? and what moved me to come hither? did none ask me to come? this they asked me often: and I Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, I would not accuſe any. And I ſaid I had liberty to come here as well as to another place: For that I was not under any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint: They ſaid no, that was true: But what moved me to come hither? and to this many ſpeak at once; And I ſaid, are you all Speakers at once againſt me? I will ſpeak to the civileſt of you, and ſo directed my ſpeech to one: Then they asked me whether an extraordinary impulſe was that which moved me to come? I told them, as to this I would not tell them, for that I knew they were not capable of ſuch things; And one of theſe Juſtices that queſtioned me, his name is Mr. <hi>Launce,</hi> one of <hi>Holland Simp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> Church people, a very unlovely walker, little ſign of member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in him; yet he would undertake diſcourſe concerning the Spirits impulſes; But as ſome of their own ſaid, this diſcourſe gravelled them, and ſoon made them give over; they had no more to ſay, but run into confuſion, only ſome uttered a few envious deriding expreſſions, calling me dreamer. I ſaid ſo <hi>Joſeph</hi> was called. And then one Major <hi>Selly</hi> calls two women, that ſaid they would take their Oaths I ſhould ſay I knew the Juſtices were with me that day beforementioned, the which was falſe; and when they were called, one fell in a ſwound, and the other run away;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:118503:33"/>But I told him that there might be falſe witneſſes brought againſt me; and ſo had Chriſt and the Apoſtles: therefore that was no wonder to be dealt ſo with: they commanded one to be indited, and the Jayler was bid take him, for but looking chearfully, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of my friends, they ſaid he laughed at them: I then asked them whether they lay upon the Catch, and would make a man an offender for nothing; thus I have as brief as I could, given you a Relation, omitting many ſeveral paſſages for another opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and what I apprehended moſt obſervable, I have now Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, that you may take notice of the horns running at my breſt; which as touching me, much hath been fulfilled. My two ſureties, one ſtanding on the one ſide of me, and the other on the other ſide when the horn run at me; they, or the Lord through them, ſaid, <hi>I will be thy ſafety,</hi> an arm and a hand claſping me round. Obſerve this I pray in the Book. Captain <hi>Langdons</hi> Salutes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to you and your wife; My Salutes and dear reſpects to you and to my dear ſiſter, your wife; and Salutes to my brother and ſiſter <hi>Powel,</hi> and to Captain <hi>Harriſon</hi> your brother, and to <hi>Betty,</hi> and to my <hi>Stripling:</hi> I beg your praiſes for me, and Prayer without ceaſing: She will not herein be wanting for you, who is greatly obliged to ſerve you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Anna Trapnel.</signed>
               <dateline>From Capt. <hi>Langdons</hi> at <hi>Tregaſow</hi> near <hi>Trurow:</hi> 
                  <date>the fourteenth of the ſecond Moneth, 1654.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>From the Priſon to the Priſon at <hi>Windſor</hi> Caſtle, the ſixth of the third Moneth. 1654.</head>
            <p>DEar brothers, with your wives: Salutes preſented: its no ſmall joy to me, the hearing your Faith, Confidence, Courage and Stedfaſt unſhaken frame of Spirit which you abide in, the which I hope will continue to the end: and that it may mount, prayer is without ceaſing in your behalf: and Faith is very ſtrong and bold to affirm for that Zeal you have held out, that it is not <hi>Jehu</hi> like, but <hi>Jeſus</hi> like, bearing his ſtamp on it: which no ſufferings, nor hard harſh dealings can ſhake: neither can any inſinuating, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, ſmooth, fine words change and alter a well grounded faith and reſolution for the great ſure and abiding Protector: (its not great proffers of fat Benefices, amounting to an hundred by the year that ſhall beguile you of a reward: that is far more then thouſands or ten thouſands a year) But <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> word of this is caution
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:118503:34"/>enough to you, whom I am confident hath overcome the evil one, as to that and many other reſpects, I hope.</p>
            <p>Yet theſe being trying times, <hi>Cedars</hi> have need to be put in mind that the root beareth them, and not they the root, and its well that it is ſo: For were it not for the Root, eſtabliſhing and building up work would be ſoon decayed, eſpecially in trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome times: he or ſhe that ſtandeth, have need to look to their Foundation: Not in reſpect of what is already: but ſure there is a darker Cloud, and a rougher Sea at hand, and greater will be the Billows yet: A bluſtering tribulation time muſt be expected before we ſee our haven: But all that love Chriſt in ſincerity will not ſhrink, whatever pinchings they meet with: Knowing that their Redemption will ſufficiently requite and recrute them.</p>
            <p>My Lord, for whoſe ſake I am in mans Priſon, is very free, and ſupplieth all my wants, and continually he feaſts my ſoul, his goings forth are prepared as the morning, and he is to me as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and latter rain, and he leaveth me not without ſap one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: ſure I ſhall bleſs the Lord, the good hand of the Lord, for leading me down to <hi>Cornwel:</hi> while I live I ſhall praiſe for the ſpecial favours I have ſeen, and I ſhall magnifie free grace for the double inlargements that hath been enjoyed in Priſon; its a place of melody, joy unſpeakable and full of glory, in believing.</p>
            <p>I never found ſo much of Divine preſence without interruption, as ſince my Lodge in <hi>Plimouth</hi> Fort: (Oh friends, its a very high honor to ſuffer for well-doing) for then neither God nor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will condemn, and then what can hinder boldneſs with God? (and for him.)</p>
            <p>The Clergy hath ſtirred up the Magiſtrate, and they command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Souldiery, which ſoon acted; a Fox being a Kinſman to the chief Ruler, cries out, come ſee my Zeal for thy Government! though I medled not with him, nor his government: but my work ſince I came into the Weſt, hath been a holding out what I ſaw and heard from Scripture, touching the New Covenant, as concerning ſinners and poor tempted ſouls: and the Reign of King Jeſus his Laws and Miniſtry: and this was held out in that extraordinary di<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>penſation that you ſaw and heard of: which hath been very little abſent from me ſince I ſaw you, which is to the wonder of my own particular, and of many others, that my health, ſtrength and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral life is preſerved under ſo much fillings and actings; but how beholding am I, and all the Family of God with me are engaged
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:118503:34"/>with me to Chriſt Jeſus, who is all in all: and ſure its for Sions ſake that I cannot hold my peace.</p>
            <p>And may not I ſpeak in my Chamber, and ſing on my Bed, and pray on my Knees? doth the Lord forwarn me, doth Scripture for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid me? or will the General Aſſembly of the firſt born reprove me, or the particular Church I walk with, will they be offended, or will you my Father be angry, or you my brother be diſpeaſed? I beſeech you then let me know it, for I would not offend Jew nor Gentile, but eſpecially the Church of Chriſt: but indeed as for the ſtumbling Jew, the fooliſh Greek, the blind Gentile, the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Prieſt, againſt theſe there muſt come out the wiſdom of God, and the power of God: though it be counted fooliſhneſs, non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, witchcraft, and a white Devil, as ſuch are the terms of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Women, Learned Clergy, Self-ſeeking Rulers in theſe parts; hearing their ſubtile Fox at <hi>Pendenis</hi> Caſtle, to aid and aſſiſt with his Squadron of Souldiers, and the fierceſt grim looked ones muſt be the Conveyers to Priſon, that ſo the Clergy may be pleaſed; and this was their envy, becauſe I ſaw their downfal, and told of it, they could not abide me: but that which made them cry out, was their <hi>Diana</hi> Tythe; this gain brought to them by the Rulers, makes them cry up the fourth <hi>Monarchy,</hi> not that they care for them, but its theirs that they are greedy after, and that maketh the Prieſt take falſe oaths, or do any thing to ingratiate with the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, that ſo they may put into their mouths; but their time will not be long I am confident, for their horn groweth blunt pointed: it will ere long be broken to pieces, it cannot laſt many years, for woe, and great fury is againſt them, being the greateſt enemies Chriſt hath in <hi>England,</hi> and they make the poor Countries drunk with their Fornication. Oh therefore lament and mourn, and pray down this abomination, and bleſs God that you are come off from the Adulterers function, and take heed of medling with a hoof of that beaſt any more!</p>
            <p>I believe you never ſaw nor felt that horn as I have done ſince I came from <hi>London,</hi> but if as to my hurt the puſhing had been, I would have been ſilent, I am ſure I ſhould: but ſeeing its againſt the Prieſtly office, and prophetical and Kingly cower of King Jeſus, I muſt declare for him, and while I have tongue and breath it ſhall go forth for the fifth <hi>Monarchy</hi>-Laws teaching and practice: Oh let not life be more valued then it! ſhall we think too much for <hi>the chiefeſt of ten thouſands?</hi> (God forbid.)</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:118503:35"/>
            <p>My dear Brothers and Siſters, your beloved wives, I beg leave to encourage you, and to comfort you with my comfortable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, being perſwaded they are for your ſakes: And oh that you may be ſtrengthned thereby, hearing of a poor Shrub, one of a timerous, fearful, cowardly nature: and in her own concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments no whit valorous the Lord knoweth, but as for the Lords concernments I ſee fierce Rulers, and reviling Prieſts, and mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rude multitude, and Swords and Guns do not, nor hath not ſo much as cauſed the leaſt damp to ariſe in me, but I praiſe that ſuch a vile unworthy Creature as I, ſhould have ſo much honor inferr'd upon me.</p>
            <p>I never was ſure ſo much in ſelf-loathing and abhorring as now: If that the Trial of faith be ſo precious, what is faith it ſelf? but what is that object then for whom its tryed? I pray reſt on him, and abide faithful to the end: for I know he will Crown you with Deliverance and Conqueſt; Fight under his Banners he will not forſake you; wait, for you ſhall not be aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: you ſhall ſee the end of your faith, and your tongue ſhall ſay, let the Lord be magnified; Praiſe ye the Lord for me, and Pray for me a poor ſilly Creature, in whom the Lord is ſeen: I have nothing to glory in, ſave in infirmities: Pray that I may not be proud of ſufferings, I have a baſe heart; but the Lord through Grace maketh me for the preſent more then a Conqueror: Pray that I may continue; I dare not ſay, if all deny Chriſt, I will not: Yet through his ſtrength I ſhall not love my life to the death; and I have believed, therefore have I ſpoken, and I believe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpeak, and the Lord our God increaſe our Fai<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h. <hi>Amen,</hi> ſo be it, ſaith your ſiſter in the Faith and Fellowſhip of the Goſpel.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Anna Trapnel.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>For the Lords Priſoner at <hi>Windſor</hi> Caſtle. From the ſame Lords Priſoner at <hi>Plimouth</hi> Fort, who is to be ſent by Sea I do not know when; But I am to be conveyed to <hi>Portchmouth,</hi> and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſaith to the Council, and ſo to be dealt with according to Juſtice; but I know not what their Juſtice is: But I am ſure their true Juſtice ſhall make them know what it is in due time; I am no fearful nor careful as to what they may ſay and do: The Lord and his Council is on my ſide, that ſhall be my defence for ever.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:118503:35"/>
            <head>To the Church ſometimes meeting at <hi>All-hallows</hi> the Great, in <hi>Thames-ſtreet,</hi> In LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Dear</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BRothers and Siſters; Grace, Mercy and Peace I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded are your companions. And its no ſmall joy to me; Neither is it a little matter in my eſteem, to be taken in, and reckoned one of your companions in the ſweet and lovely Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Goſpel; And that upon that noble account of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Communion with Chriſt. Which Principle you do well to look unto, that nothing take it away from you; For ſure it is a Crown worth the prizing; And will, and doth make you as a Beakon on a Hill lighted: And if this Crown be let go, then An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts rigid thorny Crown will be advanced by you, and I, you will put your ſelves out of a capacity of doing and receiving that good which I am ſure this Goſpel Principle affords, and honors you with; But of that I need ſay no more, for I know you are taught of God, and being ſo, I know you are not unwilling to be put in mind by your unworthy ſiſter, whom I am ſure hath a dear, honored, honouring, reſpectfull love to you in her heart, and where-ever ſhe goeth; And ſaying often to the Lord, what am I, that thou ſhouldeſt put me among thoſe children? I am melted by loves flame, and in the ſuns thaw and heat; I through Grace now write unto you my beloved friends; that though your unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſiſter be in a Priſon here at <hi>Plimouth</hi> Fort, its for the matters and concernments of King Jeſus. Therefore I am perſwaded it will be no blemiſh to your dear Fellowſhip, the which I prize more then my liberty or life, If I know my own heart: Sure I have cauſe to bleſs God for your Prayers, for I know I have much bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thereby; Not now only, but ever ſince I ſaw you. O my friends! Pray! Pray! Pray ſtill for her which never ceaſeth Praying for
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:118503:36"/>you; even when my bodily ſenſes ſleepeth, my Spirit hath Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with you, and for you. I never had ſo many ſmiles, and ſuch conſtant intimate familiarity with God, as ſince my outward im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment: O that you were all as I am, except my bonds, for its a condition worth the high eſteem of you all; But ſhall I boaſt of Viſions, and Revelations, and Faith wound up very high? I will not hereof boaſt; But of free Grace I will think, and ſpeak, and praiſe, and give thanks, and let me herein engage you alſo; and Chriſts love to his friends; I beſeech you for his ſake do not be ſilent, hold not your peace day nor night, till <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> be made the praiſe of the whole earth. You have a priſe put into your hands, lay hold: O do not let it go! They that draw back, the Lord will have no pleaſure in; He cannot abide tottering frames of ſpirit; He no way approves of a ſetting the hand to the Plow, and falling back again to a lazy idle ſtate, they are not like to attain to that ſtature Scripture ſpeaks of; which is better then worldly ſtate, and dying pomp, and withering proſperity, and fading gallantry. What will they do, who takes up, ſpends, and waſts away that time which ſure is precious? Dear friends, you probably may hear divers reports concerning me, from that falſe evil ſpirits raiſing in theſe parts, and ſending their Rumerous ſound into thoſe <hi>Eaſtern</hi> parts, which I know hath grieved many of you; though as to the harboring of Reports againſt me, whereby to be preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced concerning the work of the Lord in me, and magnified by me: I am perſwaded you will not receive any thing of ſuch like nature; which hath the Spawn of Satan in it: But I would not vindicate my ſelf, were it not for truths ſake. But however I leave my own particular with the truth, who will vindicate it ſelf and me too at the concluſion. For the which I am made willing by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſtrength to wait, and not compulſively, but willingly; For I know him in whom I truſt will ſtand by me. And indeed he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with me; againſt enemies within and without, what I have ſuffered ſince I ſaw you: For the Lord thereby, he is ſtill putting on more of that cloathing of humility which my ſoul exceedingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and pray friends do you beg this for me too, and that I may not be proud of Sufferings: Methinks they are high honors. I ſure am unworthy to be ſo honored: but O how beholding am I to Chriſt and his worthineſs! and to that I look: and I know he keepeth me, elſe I ſhould ſoon depart from him and his ways; I
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:118503:36"/>ſtand not one moment but by Omnipotent power; And of this he maketh me largely to experience: I may admire his love: Many ways it hath let out its imbraces; I will not fear what men can do unto me, for I am not ready to be bound, but to dye: I ſpeak not a <hi>Pauls</hi> word, but the Lord knows I ſpeak from ſeeing, hearing, taſting and feeling that which maketh my heart live: And I know that Chriſt lives in me, and the life that I live is by the faith of the Son of God, who dyed and gave himſelf for me: and the knowledge of this makes ſouls active for him, not only to honor him in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but to glorifie him in the fires: And if any be caſt into Priſon by Satan, either inwardly or outwardly, if it be for Chriſt, they ſhall have great joy: and though I could not count it all joy when I was in Satans horrible Pit; Yet for that ſorrow occaſioned by him, I have had abundance of joy, and can and do account it a choice pearl in my Crown that I am now Crowned with, which is freely given to me, not only to believe, but to ſuffer; and truly this ſecond Priſon of Satans is a joyfull one not onely to me, but to many ſpectators. My dear brothers and ſiſters, you mourned while I was in that laſt years Priſon. But I beſeech you rejoyce and be glad, that your unworthy ſiſter hath liberty and enlargement in a Priſon; I ſhould rejoyce to ſee your faces, and enjoy that ſweet Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in Gods Sanctuary, but though abſent in body, I am ſure I am not ſo in Spirit, and the thoughts of this affords me great content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: For I cannot ſay woe is me, becauſe I am not in <hi>Meſech,</hi> neither am I an inhabitant in the Tents of <hi>Kedar:</hi> For the Lord is a Sanctuary here as well as in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> and I know if he carry me <hi>Weſt, Eaſt, North</hi> or <hi>South,</hi> he will not let me fall: But if my ſelf or Creature carry me, I durſt not be ſo confident, My dear friends, bear with my boldneſs for Chriſt; I am ſure I have a baſhfull nature, and as to my own matters I am not forward. Do I herein juſtifie my ſelf? I do not, but I praiſe the Lord, and our Father that keepeth me: whatſoever any beſmearings are, he waſhing open Fountain waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away. And I ſee all thing working for good, though I come very ſhort of my duty to God-ward, and indeed I may cry, O my barrenneſs and un<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fulneſs, and that truly, for I tail much the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of ſo many ſhowers of mercy, in that I am ſo little in bringing forth fruit; But I can ſay m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſires are large, Pray then! O pray to our Father to fulfill ſuch deſires, which is a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter much: Sanctifie, that I may glorifie him in Soul, Body and Spirit, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:118503:37"/>the Lords; I would not be my own, nor for my own things; I would be, and be for the Lord: intreat that I may hold out to the end, notwithſtanding all rage or rages. I ſhall give you a fuller ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of my demeanor when the Lord brings me to ſee you, which ſure I ſhall do, though many ſeek my life: <hi>They that looſe their life for King Jeſus ſake, ſhall take it up again,</hi> and they that cowardly <hi>ſeeks to ſave it, ſhall looſe it.</hi> I ſent you a Letter from the <hi>Weſt,</hi> in one to brother <hi>Gardner:</hi> wherein I deſired your Counſel and Exhortation, but I have no Anſwer: I believe you do not forget me; Yet I am grieved you do not write to me now in my bonds. But I am perſwaded they are made eaſie through your Prayer; if I any way offend you, tell me, that I may do ſo no more; but if any are not perſwaded concerning the extraordinary diſpenſation that hath been, and is ſtill upon me: I am ſorry that any ſhould be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at ſuch Soul-raviſhing, Sin-ſubduing, Creature-Crucifying, Chriſt-Exalting Ordinance, Loving Enjoyments. If any of theſe be not prized, and endeavoured after by me, then chide me: O ſpare not to reprove me, for in many things I offend: But my dear friends, if Chriſts eye raviſheth, I muſt ſing; If he open the mouth, it will Pray; if the Spirit ſay come, the Brid ſaith ſo to; and they that hear utter, come Lord Jeſus, come quickly: I am taking my Voyage, Time and Tyde will not tarry: I take my leave, Pray for my journey from <hi>Portchmouth,</hi> and for courage to bring me to the Council. I have much at the preſent I bleſs God. Farewell my dear friends, <hi>I Reſt,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Engaged ſiſter in the Spirit, and Faith, and Fellowſhip of the Goſpel. <hi>Anna Trapnel.</hi> Who deſires not to be her own, but the Lords and his Peoples. For Whole Sion ſhe ſuffers, with whole Sion ſhe ſhall Reign: Though unworthy.</signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>Plimouth</hi> Fort in haſte, going ſtrait with Captain <hi>Kendal</hi> a States Ship to <hi>Portchmouth.</hi> 
                  <date>This 8 of the 3 Moneth. 1654.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
